<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ's government in and over his people. Delivered in a sermon before the Honourable House of Commons, at their late publick and solemne fast, Octob. 26. 1642. / By Thomas Temple D.D. and minister of the Church of Battersea in Surrey. Published by order of that House.</title>
            <author>Temple, Thomas, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E127_37</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4760</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872718</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156219</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95617)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156219)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E127[37])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ's government in and over his people. Delivered in a sermon before the Honourable House of Commons, at their late publick and solemne fast, Octob. 26. 1642. / By Thomas Temple D.D. and minister of the Church of Battersea in Surrey. Published by order of that House.</title>
                  <author>Temple, Thomas, d. 1661.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Gellibrand at the Brazen Serpent in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons.</note>
                  <note>Order to print on verso of first leaf, dated 26 October [1642].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms II, 6 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:156219:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Die Mercurii 26. Octobris.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Houſe of Commons, That Sir <hi>Francis Knollis</hi> doe returne thanks from this Houſe to Doctor <hi>Temple</hi> for the great paines he took in the Sermon he preached at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of the ſaid Houſe, at St. Margarets in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Weſtminſter, this preſent day of publick humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that he be deſired to print his Sermon. And it is Ordered, that no man ſhall preſume to print it, but he who ſhall be authorized under the ſaid Doctor <hi>Temple's</hi> hand writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>I appoint SAMUEL GELLIBRAND to print my Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THO. TEMPLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156219:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRIST'S GOVERNMENT In and over his PEOPLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Delivered in</hi> A SERMON Before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS, At their late publick and ſolemne Faſt, <hi>Octob.</hi> 26. 1642.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Thomas Temple</hi> D. D. and Miniſter of the Church of <hi>Batterſea</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of that Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 97.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord reigneth, let the earth rejoyce: let the multitude of the Iſles be glad thereof.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for SAMUEL GELLIBRAND at the Brazen Serpent in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:156219:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156219:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing called to this ſervice by your command, I could not think of a fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubject, &amp; more ſeaſonable to the times and your places then this, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Kingdom of Chriſt: firſt, to ſet before you the chiefe employment God cals you to, and the duty lies upon you in it, that is, to ſtudy all the waies by which Ieſus Chriſt may be beſt ſetled in his throne, and his government moſt ſpread throughout theſe parts of the world, where your work lies. Secondly, to hold out unto you the great encouragement to ſo great a work, in which you are ſure to meet with ſo great oppoſitions; to let you know, God himſelf will carry it on, and Chriſts government ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, notwithſtanding the rage of people, and the plots of Princes againſt the Lord and his Annointed. If you go on in this cauſe with upright hearts, there is no reaſon your ſpirits ſhould faint, or your hands ſlacken in fear of the iſſue: you are on a riſing ſide, and in a work that
<pb facs="tcp:156219:3"/>will improve it ſelf. And indeed you have need of encouragement, even from heaven, to go on in the work of reformation of the Chuch, and of eſtabliſhing Chriſts government amongſt us, where the endeavours of many are ſo mighty to oppoſe it, and their tongues ſo malignant to diſgrace it. But while your hearts are faithfull with God, reſolve to goe on with Gods work, knowing <hi>you muſt paſſe through evill report as well as good report.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.8.</note> They who are called to great works, muſt be willing to ſacrifice all, eſtate, credit, life, in the cauſe of God: ſo we keep faith and peace with God, and doe not ſhipwrack a good conſcience, it matters not much what elſe we loſe. If Chriſt carry you through the work here, he is all-ſufficient to reward you hereafter. The Lord make <hi>all great mountaines that lie in your way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iac. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>to the ſetting up of the Kingdom of Chriſt, as plaines before you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.2.</note> and in the end, <hi>reward your works, and your labour, and your patience;</hi> So praies,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study in Batterſea,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 6. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The unworthieſt of the ſervants of Chriſt in the work of the Lord,</hi> THOMAS TEMPLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156219:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before The Honourable Houſe of COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT, At the publick Faſt, <hi>Octob.</hi> 26. 1642.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 2.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſecond pſalme is an exact deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kingdome of Chriſt, as it was propheſied of by <hi>David,</hi> who was himſelfe a type and figure of Chriſt in his Kingdome, and the Father of him according to the fleſh: which, as it appeares out of the frame of the whole pſalme, ſo we finde this Pſalme clearly expounded of Chriſt and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by the Apoſtles in the new Teſtament. Firſt, where mention is made of the Heathens rage, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156219:4"/>the Kings of the earth bandying <hi>againſt the Lord and his Annoynted, v.</hi> 1.2. this is by the whole Colledge of Apoſtles and Diſciples, expounded of <hi>Chriſt, Act.</hi> 4.25.27. Secondly, where it is ſaid, <hi>thou art my ſon, this day have I begotten thee, v.</hi> 7. this is alſo plainly expounded of Chriſt, not of his birth, as it ſeemes to be meant upon the firſt view, but of his reſurrection from the grave, which is as it were a new begetting, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.33. A fit ſubject of our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, as in all other, ſo eſpecially in theſe times, Chriſt, as he ſtands to us in this relation of a <hi>King.</hi> we are all willing to looke upon <hi>Christ,</hi> as he ſtands in the relation of a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> offering himſelfe in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for our ſins, ſo deſiring him as a Saviour to ſave our ſoules: wee leſſe delight to eye him as a <hi>Prophet</hi> revealing Gods will to us, little careing to know him: but wee commonly hate to thinke upon him as a <hi>King,</hi> as not eaſilie ſubjecting our ſelves to be governed by him. I ſhall therfore crave your attention, while I unfold to you this peice of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>The Pſalm conſiſts of three main parts: Firſt it ſets forth the mad and furious councells and attempts of wicked people againſt Chriſt,<note place="margin">Act 5.39. affectaſſe fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt regnum celeſte gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantes.</note> who feare not to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, like the old Giants, fighters againſt God himſelfe: their rage and malice is bent even againſt the God that made and redeemed them: <hi>why doe the Heathen rage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>and the people imagine a vaine thing? The Kings of the earth ſet themſelves, &amp; the Rulers take councell together againſt the Lord and againſt his Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ncynted.</hi> Secondly, it ſets forth Gods eſtabliſhment of Chriſt in his Kingdom; notwithſtanding all the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156219:4"/>attempts of wicked men againſt him, yet nothing ſhall overthrow his Kingdome, but on the other ſide, be ſhall breake his enimies in peices: <hi>yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Sion.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">ver. 6.</note> It conteynes an exhortation, becauſe wee cannot overthrow Chriſts Kingdom, therfore to entertaine it in our hearts, to ſerve him and feare him, as wee ſeare to be deſtroyed and deſire to be bleſt: <hi>Be wiſe now therfore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 10.</note> 
               <hi>O yee Kings, be inſtructed, yee Iudges of the earth, ſerve the Lord with feare, and rejoyce with trembling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words of my text, you ſee, are the ſecond part of this Pſalme, and have their dependance upon the former, that, notwithſtanding all the machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of wicked people, God will have a King to rule in his Church, which no power of man ſhall ever overthrow. I ſhall obſerve to you three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars out of this Scripture, the King, his Throne, his Settlement in his Throne. 1 The King,<note place="margin">as ver. 7.</note> Jeſus Chriſt, God the Son, the ſecond perſon in Trinitie, God over all, bleſſed for ever. 2. his Throne, where hee ſitts, or his Kingdome where hee reignes, with the qualification of it, <hi>his holy hill of Sion:</hi> Mount Sion was a high mountaine in Jeruſalem, on the top whereof was a ſtrong Fort, which the Jebuſites kept by force from Iſrael till <hi>Davids</hi> daies, who after tooke it and fortified it and called it <hi>Davids Cittie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 11.4.</note> Neere unto which was mount Moriah,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 13 1. Neh. 11.1. Iſa 52 1. Ioel 3.17. Pſal. 78.68. Iſa. 2.3. Iſa 60.14. Heb. 12.22. Rev. 14.1.</note> where <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> after built the Temple. Wherupon Jeruſalem was called the <hi>holy Cittie:</hi> and Sion named the <hi>holy mountaine,</hi> which <hi>God loved:</hi> and from which the <hi>the Law ſhould come forth:</hi> and thence a type and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Chriſts Church. 3. The ſettlement of this King in his Throne, <hi>yet have I ſet my King,</hi> how great
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156219:5"/>ſoever the oppoſitions made by wicked men be, yet his throne is firmely eſtabliſhed. The reſults of all which are theſe, which I ſhall preſent in this order.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> Chriſt the ſecond perſon of the Trinitie is by the deſignation of his Father, appointed to be King of his Church: a King to rule and governe all thoſe whom hee hath redeemed to be a people for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> The Kingdome of Chriſt ſhall overtop the plots of wicked men, and be eſtabliſhed firmely notwithſtanding all their oppoſitions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>3</label> The Church of God, where Chriſt ſitts and reignes as King, muſt be a holy Church.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the three mayn branches which ſpring from this ſtock, the three mayn ſtreames which flow from this fountaine. The firſt:
<q>Chriſt the ſecond perſon &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> For the better underſtanding of which, wee muſt know, there is a twofold Kingdom of God: the one generall, termed the Kingdome of power and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, wherby,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.35.</note> as God the Creator, he governs the world and all things in it. The other ſpeciall, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as God the Redeemer, hee exerciſeth an admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of rule and government over the elect, by a ſpeciall name called <hi>the Kingdome of Chriſt;</hi> in which he diſpenſes to his children both grace and glory. Whence, though the diviſion be uſuall into the Kingdom of grace, and the Kingdom of glory, yet they are not two Kingdomes, but parts of one and the ſame Kingdom of Chriſt. When therfore wee ſpeake of Chriſts Kingdom, wee meane not that which he hath by nature, the government of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156219:5"/>which is univerſall over all the world, and doth agree to him as hee is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> God coeſſentiall with the Father: But that Kingdom which he hath by ſpeciall deſignation from his Father, and which is appropriated to him as he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> God and man, God with us, cloathed in our fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Chriſt the mediator; and which he diſpences as he is the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and head of that people, which he hath by his own bloud purchaſed to be a peculiar people unto God from the reſt of the world. This the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſet forth plentifully unto us in thoſe ſeverall expreſſions of <hi>giving all things into Chriſts hand, of committing all judgment to him, of Crowning him, of putting all things under his feet.</hi> Into whoſe hand hath he given all things that concerne the Church? into the hand of Chriſt, to be diſpenſed by him, <hi>he loveth him, and hath given all things into his hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 3.35.</note> To whom hath he committed all Judgment? to the Son; to him he hath committed the diſpenſing of that power which belongs originally to himſelf, <hi>the Father judgeth no man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>but hath committed all judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Son.</hi> Who is the crowned King of Gods people? Chriſt, under him all things are put in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, <hi>he hath Crowned him, and put all things under his feet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.7.</note> See what a glorious deſcription of Chriſts deſignation to this Kingdom we have, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6, 7. <hi>unto us a child is borne; unto us a ſon is given, and the government ſhall be upon his ſhoulder, and his name ſhall be called, wonderfull, couneellour, the mightie God, the everlaſting father, the Prince of peace. of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of his government and peace there ſhall be no end, upon the throne of David and upon his Kingdom, to order it and to eſtabliſh it with Iudgment &amp; with Iuſtice,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156219:6"/>from henceforth even for ever</hi> Hee, who is God the Son, the ſecond perſon in Trinity, the child borne for our Redemption, upon his ſhoulder is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment laid: as he firſt bare upon his ſhoulder his Croſſe, ſo now he beares the government of his Church upon his ſhoulder, which he purchaſed by his Croſſe. He is not only Chriſt the Saviour, but alſo Chriſt the Lord,<note place="margin">Luke 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſet upon the Throne of his father <hi>David</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>In the further opening of which poynt, I ſhall firſt ſhew you the quality of this Kingdome of Chriſts. Secondly, the grounds and reaſons why God would not governe his people in the generall way, as he governs all the world, but would have ſuch a ſolemne adminiſtration of a Kingdom by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">The quality of Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note> the quality of Chriſts Kingdom: as <hi>Samuel</hi> when he annoynted <hi>Saul</hi> King, told the people the manner of the Kingdom, ſo wee are here to inquire the manner and quality of the Kingdom of Chriſt. The Scriptures ſet it forth under two notions: firſt, that it is a Kingdom in us; Secondly, a Kingdom over us: Chriſt reigns in us, Chriſt reigns over us.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſt reigne in us. Dan. 7.13.</note>1 Chriſt reignes in us: this is that which was typified in <hi>Daniels</hi> viſion, <hi>I ſaw in the night <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and behold one like the ſon of man, and there was given him Dominion, and glory, and a Kingdom, that all people and nations and languages ſhould ſerve him.</hi> what kind of Dominion and Kingdom was this, in which all nations &amp; languages ſhould ſerve Chriſt? not an earthly Kingdom: no, that Kingdom which was given to the ſon of man in that viſion, it was a ſpirituall kingdom, the ſeting up of the Scepter of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156219:6"/>Chriſt in our hearts; <hi>my Kingdom is not of this world:</hi> it is in the world, but not of the world:<note place="margin">Iohn 18.36.</note> it is a government erected in the hearts of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>The Kingdom of God is within you;</hi> every holy heart is Chriſts throne where he ſits,<note place="margin">Luke 17.21</note> 
               <hi>the forces of the Gentiles ſhall come in unto him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 60.5.</note> In former times Chriſts Kingdom was confined to <hi>Iudea;</hi> but ſince Chriſts comming the Gentiles are called the forces of the Gentiles: the maine ſtrengths and greateſt parts of the Gentiles at ſome time or other ſhall acknowledge Chriſt. That was the voyce of the ſeaventh Angell that ſounded,<note place="margin">Revel. 11.15.</note> 
               <hi>the Kingdoms of this world are become the Kingdoms of the Lord and of Chriſt:</hi> thoſe kingdoms which were but kingdoms of this world, earthly kingdoms, that knew none but an earthly King, and yeilded no obedience but an externall obedience, now become the kingdoms of Chriſt, ſubmit themſelves to the Goſpel of Chriſt, advance his Scepter among them, and yeild obedience to his lawes; it is true, all perſons of all nations receive not Chriſt as King: but there is no nation, but hath or ſhall have Chriſts Throne ſet up among them, Chriſt ſhall have ſome ſubjects there: ſome in the houſhold of <hi>Caeſar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 4.22.</note> 
               <hi>all the Saints ſalute you, cheifly they that are of Caeſars houſhold,</hi> though not <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelfe, yet there were Saints in his houſhold that acknowledged him.<note place="margin">Acts 8.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> In the Court of the Queene of Aethiopia one Eunuch that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the faith, as God promiſed of old, <hi>turne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ſer. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>O backſliding children, I am married to you, I will take you one of a City, and two of a family, and bring you to Sion:</hi> ſo now, if God call not all, yet he will call ſome in every place, heere one and there one, heere
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156219:7"/>one in a family, and there two in a Citty, and bring them to Sion. And there are ſeverall acts, wherein this kingdom of Chriſts, that is within us, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In giving his people lawes of life, and gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by them: as there is in every King a legiſlative power, a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to make and eſtabliſh, and publiſh lawes; ſuch a power, but farre greater has Chriſt to make and eſtabliſh lawes for the government of his people: this is called by the Pſalmiſt, the ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of <hi>the rod of Chriſts ſtrength out of Sion:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.2.</note> which the Prophets <hi>Eſay</hi> and <hi>Micah</hi> both expound touching the law, which is the ſtrength of a King, <hi>Out of Sion ſhall go forth the law, and the word of the Lord from Ieruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.3. Mica 4.2.</note> But further, here is the act and exerciſe of Chriſts government in giving lawes, not that he gives any laws, but that he gives laws of life. Chriſt might give us ſuch laws, as God ſaies he gave the rebellious Iſraelites for their ſins,<note place="margin">Ezek 20.25.</note> 
               <hi>Statutes that were not good, and judgements whereby they ſhould not live:</hi> whether it be meant the ceremoniall laws that were unprofitable to lead them to heaven, or what other laws ſoever, precepts God gave them that were in ſome reſpect or other not good for them, ſtatutes in which they could not have life: ſuch Chriſt might give us now, ſtatutes and precepts that are not good, that might be burthenſom or unprofitable, not leading to life. But the laws Chriſt gives, they are laws leading to life,<note place="margin">Ezck. 20.11. Levi. 16.5. Gal. 3.12.</note> ſtatutes and judgements, <hi>which if a man do, he ſhall even live in them.</hi> Tis true indeed, by the corruption of our natures, the law may prove to our deſtruction,<note place="margin">Tom. 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>the commandment which was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to life, I found to be unto death; for ſin taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156219:7"/>by the commandment, deceived me, and by it ſlew me.</hi> Though the law <hi>per ſe</hi> of it ſelf leads and is ordained to life, yet the corruption of nature, ſtirring up the heart to break the law, does thereby <hi>ex accidenti</hi> and occaſionally turn the edge of the law againſt us to condemne us, which would have been to ſave us.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>The law is holy, and juſt, and good:</hi> ſince Chriſts laws are holy laws, the end of which is to work holineſſe in us; and juſt laws, which preſcribe nothing but what is equall for all to obey; and good laws, ſetting forth the goodneſſe of God to us in them, and winning us to goodneſſe by them; they muſt needs be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged laws of life in themſelves, ſuch as lead to life if kept, as for that end propoſed by Chriſt, not to lead to our deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In working graces in the hearts of his people: Chriſt may give laws, but if withall hee work not grace in our hearts, if he give not power to keep thoſe laws, we ſhall never obſerve them; it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a ſecond part of his Office as King, to give us grace and ſtrength to do what he propoſeth to us to be done. A wicked man, in whoſe heart Chriſt has not yet ſet up his Kingdome, looks upon Chriſts laws as ſtrange things, as God ſpeaks by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>I have written to them the great things of my law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>and they were accounted as a ſtrange thing:</hi> ſuch a man looks on Chriſts laws as ſtrange things that concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him nor, things he neither can, neither hath any will to do: but when Chriſt comes, as a King, to ſuch a man, he puts an inward love and inclination into his heart to thoſe laws, and a ſtrength to keep them. That is part of the new covenant, which God makes with us, and Chriſt enables to keep, <hi>I will put my
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156219:8"/>lawes into your minds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 31.33. Heb. 8.10.</note> 
               <hi>and write them in your hearts.</hi> Gods lawes are at firſt out of the minds of people, they are only written in our books: when Chriſt comes to us as a King, thoſe lawes he writ with his own finger upon Mount Sinai in tables of ſtone, he now writes with the finger of his ſpirit in the tables of our hearts: thoſe laws which he put into the Ark, there to be laid up for ever, he now puts into the Ark of our hearts never to be forgotten. This is the excellency of Chriſt above <hi>Moſes: Moſes</hi> is but the ſervant of Gods houſe,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.5.</note> Chriſt the Son is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in and over the houſe: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſets the lawes before us, Chriſt over awes and enables the ſpirit to keep them. <hi>Moſes</hi> preſcribes the feare of God to us,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.13.17.</note> 
               <hi>You ſhall feare the Lord your God:</hi> Chriſt as a King ſtrikes powerfully a feare into us,<note place="margin">Ier. 32.40.</note> 
               <hi>I will put my feare into your hearts. Moſes</hi> commands us to love God, <hi>thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 11.1.</note> Chriſt enables to love him,<note place="margin">Deut 30.6.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord thy God will circumciſe thy heart to love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. 2.19.</note> The circumciſion of the heart is Gods work, as the circumciſion of the fleſh is mans. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> commands to walk in Gods ſtatutes, <hi>what does the Lord thy God require of thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>but to feare the Lord, and to walk in all his wayes:</hi> but when the ſpirits of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men cannot comply with holy laws, Chriſt enables them,<note place="margin">Ezel. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>I will give them one heart, and put a new ſpirit within them, that they may walk in my ſtatutes, and keep mine ordinances,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.26.</note> 
               <hi>and do them.</hi> Chriſt not only ſets the wayes before us, but withall cauſes us to walk in them, gives us natures ſuitable and ſpirits agreeable to thoſe wayes, ſuch as ſhall delight in them. If we were to do Gods works by mans ſtrength,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156219:8"/>wee ſhould give but an ill account of our performances: we ſhould have no ſtrength for them, no delight in them: but Chriſt ſtrengthens us,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt ſtrengthning me:</hi> nay Chriſt, who works the very works in us, <hi>not I, but the grace of God in me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note> The new man under the new covenant, hath new ſtrengths: as when <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> went to annoint <hi>Saul</hi> King over Gods people, an employment he might well think too great for himſelf, <hi>Samuel</hi> withall told him, that God ſhould <hi>turne him into another man:</hi> if God turne us into other men,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 10.6.</note> and give us ſtrengths ſuitable, no works God cals us to ſhall be difficult to us. God ſet the Iſraelites in a troubleſome way to Canaan, through the mountains and deſarts; but becauſe he withall gave them <hi>his cloud by day, and his pillar of fire by night to lead them,</hi> they were able to break through all difficulties, and all incumbrances: ſo long as God gives us his own preſence to go before us, and his ſtrengths to enable us, we need not be troubled at the greatneſſe or harſhneſſe of duties. It ſhould be ours, which was St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> reſolution, <hi>da Domine quod ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, &amp; jube quod vis,</hi> ſo long as God gives ſtrength for duties, let us not be troubled whatever God requires of us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In cheriſhing the ſeeds of grace till they bee brought to a further perfection: grace is but ſmall at firſt, 'tis not with the trees of righteouſneſſe, as it was with the trees of Paradiſe, made perfect at once: grace is but like <hi>the graine of muſtardſeed,</hi> the leaſt of all ſeeds, eaſily kild, like a <hi>ſcintilla,</hi> a ſpark of fire eaſily quencht. The devill, and the world, and our owne luſts, are the thornes that choak our graces, the ſtones that hinder their radication, the birds of prey that devoure them, while they are in the ſeeds: wee have need of an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156219:9"/>power to draw them forth and perfect them. This is a work Chriſt takes into his own hand; as his hand plants and ſowes, ſo it is his hand that waters and gives the encreaſe.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.20.</note> 
               <hi>He will not break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking flax,</hi> untill he bring forth judgement unto victory: ſo farre from breaking a bruiſed ſinner, ſo farre from quenching the heat of grace that once begins to ſmoak and kindle, that on the other ſide he will carry up the work by his own ſpeciall ſtrength, he will cheriſh the ſeeds of grace, till that holy frame of grace begun in our ſouls be brought to ſuch a heigth and compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that Gods Kingdom in us ſhall be victorious over all oppoſite corruptions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. In giving new ſupplies of his ſpirit, till he bring his people to glory: 'tis not enough for us to have grace begun, but there muſt be new ſupplies of grace continued to us: 'tis not only the ſending of an influence from the Sun to the earth, but the continuing of that influence every day, muſt continue life in the creatures: there muſt be a preſerving power of grace from Chriſt, as well as a begetting power,<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.24.</note> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Thou ſhalt guide me with thy counſell, and after receive me to glory.</hi> We have need of a continuance of Chriſts counſell and direction here in the way of grace before we be received to glory. There be many paſſages of difficulty and danger we meet with in the courſe of our lives, in which we ſhall ſtick, if Chriſt ſhould not be always by us to carry us thorow. The firſt grace given us will not perhaps be ſufficient to carry us thorough great temptations and great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. A child may walk in a ſmooth way without help, but not in a rugged: the firſt meaſures of grace may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to go thorough ſmooth wayes of Chriſtianity, where little danger or difficulty is: but when it comes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156219:9"/>to a rugged way, a great triall, a great temptation, wee have then need of new ſtrength. Chriſt is like other Kings in this, 'tis not enough for him only to conquer, but he muſt fortifie, and continue garriſons to maintain his conqueſts. <hi>Bleſſed be God the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ſaies St. <hi>Peter, who hath begotten us to a lively hope of an inheritance, and who are kept by the power of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>through faith unto ſalvation.</hi> Chriſt does not only beget us, but alſo keep us by his own power through faith to ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In purifying the heart and ſubduing our luſts: that's the deſcription of the comming of Chriſt in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of grace, <hi>he ſhall come as refiners fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>and as fullers ſoap:</hi> as the fire refines the ſilver and takes away the droſſe, and as the ſoap rinſes out ſpots and ſtaines, ſo ſhall Chriſt refine and purge his people:<note place="margin">Mat. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>he ſhall baptize with the holy Ghoſt and fire, and whoſe fan is in his hand:</hi> waſh throughly and deſtroy corruptions even as fire deſtroys all that ſtands before it. Chriſts work while he was upon earth, was exerciſed much in this, in caſting out devils, <hi>if I caſt out devils by the ſpirit of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.28.</note> 
               <hi>then is the Kingdom of God come unto you:</hi> ſo it holds ſtill, when the Kingdom of God comes unto us, there will be a caſting out devils by the ſpirit of Chriſt, ſin will be diſpoſſeſt of its former holds, luſt will be ſubdued in us. When Chriſt comes into the heart, he comes with the power of a King, and the ſtrongeſt luſts, the moſt giant like corruptions ſhall not ſtand before him: as <hi>David</hi> has an expreſſion, <hi>Lift up your heads O ye gates, and be lifted up ye ever laſting doores, and the King of glory ſhall come in:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.7.</note> 
               <hi>who is this King of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? the Lord ſtrong and mighty, the Lord mighty in battell.</hi> When the King of glory, Chriſt the glorious King, mighty in battell comes into our hearts, no doores of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156219:10"/>our luſts ſhall be able to keep him out.<note place="margin">Mich. 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>He will ſubdue all our iniquities;</hi> every luſt, that it ſhall not reigne in us: <hi>Sin ſhall not have deminion over you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>for ye are not under the law but under grace.</hi> If we were only under the law, we ſhould have no power againſt our luſts; but becauſe we are under grace, under the government of Chriſt, who rules us by the grace of his ſpirit; therfore ſin ſhall not have dominion over us, ſin ſhall be ſubdued under us. Look how a conquering King comes into an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies countrey, he puls down all ſtrong holds, and breaks the power of an enemy: ſuch is the entrance of Chriſt as King into the heart, there may bee ſome ſcattering troops, the Cananites may be left in the land, but all the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſtrong holds</hi> are pul'd down,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4.</note> Chriſt breaks the ſtrength of ſin, that it ſhall not reigne in us.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In creating inward peace, and joy, and comfort: it is the office of a King to keep his ſubjects in a joyfull, a peaceable, a flouriſhing condition. <hi>The Kingdom of God conſiſts not in meat and drink</hi> (things externall) <hi>but in righteouſneſſe and peace and joy in the holy Ghoſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> Chriſt is firſt <hi>Melchiſedec King of righteouſneſſe,</hi> his government a righteous government; and then <hi>King of Salem, King of peace,</hi> a government accompanied with abundance of inward joy and peace. As peace is that crownes all other bleſſings, ſo Chriſt knowing the excellency of this, and that none could give it but himſelfe, did ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when he was to leave the earth, promiſe this as a fruit of his Kingly office to leave his diſciples this le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy of peace,<note place="margin">Iob. 14.27.</note> 
               <hi>peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you,</hi> it is Chriſts peace, not the worlds: <hi>in mee ye ſhall have peace:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.33.</note> if Chriſt ſpeak a word of peace to our harts, if he give us an anſwer of peace, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah, God ſhall give Pharoah an anſwer of peace;</hi> then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156219:10"/>though wee have tribulations in the world, wee ſhal be of good cheere, wee ſhall have comfort enough, Chriſt as King hath overcome the world, and will ſettle peace in us; that's the expedience of Chriſts goingfrom us, that he may ſend us the comforter; <hi>it is expedient that I goe away, for if I goe not away, the comforter will not come;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 15.7.</note> 
               <hi>but if I depart, I will ſend him unto you:</hi> being in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of his kingdom he ſends comfort. There is no having peace, nor joy, nor comfort, but from Chriſt, who as King is only able to allay all ſtormes and troubles, which the divell and our owne conſciences for ſin raiſe within us. It is with inward peace as it is with the outward, <hi>if he give quietneſſe, who can make trouble:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 34.29.</note> if Chriſt work quietneſſe, if he make a calme in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if <hi>he rebuke the winds and the ſea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 14.32.</note> nothing from the world can raiſe a tempeſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſts reigne over us. Mic. 4.7. Luke 1.33.</note>2 Chriſt reignes over us: <hi>the Lord ſhall reigne over them in mount Sion, he ſhall reigne over the houſe of Iacob.</hi> not only in us, but over us; not only in us for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but over us alſo for our good. This is termed by the Pſalmiſt, <hi>a ſitting on the right hand of the Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.1.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord ſaid to my Lord, ſit thou on my right hand:</hi> a phraſe to note the actuall adminiſtration of his kingdom, that as a king he ſits in great power, judging among his enimies and governing his people. And there are alſo ſeverall acts wherein the exerciſe of this part of his kingdom over us conſiſts:</p>
            <p>Firſt, in ſuppreſſing the enemies of the Church: that is the power that God gives to Chriſt as King of his Church, <hi>to rule in the midst of his enimies:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.2.</note> and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe God made to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.17.</note> 
               <hi>that his ſeed ſhould poſſeſſe the gate of his enemies.</hi> While Gods people keep covenant with God, they ſhall be ſecure, the <hi>lilly</hi> ſhall grow up
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156219:11"/>
               <hi>among the thornes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>and there ſhalbe no enchantment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 23.23.</note> 
               <hi>no divination againſt Iſrael;</hi> Chriſt ſettles his Church ſo ſtrong, <hi>that the gates of hell ſhall never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile against her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> ſhee may be aſſaulted and ſhaken, but never conquered: as the Romans loſt ſome battells, but they never loſt a war; Gods Church may have ſome foyles, but ſhee ſhall be alwayes the conquerer in the end. God commands deliverances for his people; <hi>thou art my King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 44.4.</note> 
               <hi>O God, command deliverances for Iacob:</hi> 'tis the comfort of Gods people to know, ſo long as Chriſt ſtands,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 8.20</note> his Church ſhall not fall: the people thought themſelves ſafe when they had a King to fight their bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells; ſo long as we have Chriſt to fight our battells, we need not feare; if Chriſt be for us, none can be againſt us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in beſtowing all bleſſings upon us: <hi>in him ſhall all the nations of the earth be bleſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.18.</note> all who are bleſt, are bleſt in Chriſt, who is the King, commanding bleſſings upon his people; bleſſings ſpirituall, <hi>bleſſed be God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph 1 3.</note> 
               <hi>who hath bleſt us with all ſpirituall blesſings in Chriſt:</hi> hee the head and fountaine of all ſpirituall bleſſings, bleſſings temporall; as Ioſeph was a type of Gods Church, all thoſe bleſſings which Iacob propheſied ſhould come upon the head of Ioſeph, ſhall through Chriſt come upon the head of the Church, <hi>the blesſings of heaven above, the blesſings of the deep that lye under, the blesſings of the breaſt, and the blesſings of the womb,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 49.25.</note> 
               <hi>unto the utmoſt bounds of the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hills, they ſhall be upon the head of Ioſeph,</hi> upon the head of the Church; and at laſt, the bleſſing of eternall glory in heaven,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.6.</note> when Chriſt ſhall with himſelfe make all his people who ſerve him here, <hi>Kings</hi> to reigne with him there for ever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In ſanctifying all conditions, and ordering
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156219:11"/>and turning all to the beſt for his own people: there is no condition, proſperity, adverſity, health, ſicknes, life, death, but it would be hurtfull to us, if Chriſt did not ſit as King to moderate and ſanctifie it to us. <hi>Wee know,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>all things work together for the good of them that love God, who are called according to his purpoſe;</hi> how comes it that all things work together for their good who love God and are the called of God, more then for theirs who love him not, and are not called of him? that affliction is ſanctified to the one and not to the other? as S. <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaies, you may obſerve in the ſame fire the gold ſparkles and gathers luſtre,<note place="margin">abunoigne aurum rutilat &amp; palea ſumat.</note> when the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſumes and vaniſhes to ſmoake? becauſe Chriſt ſits as King to order every thing for the beſt of his own ſubjects, and to turne every thing for the worſt to his enemies; Chriſt does for us heere as he does for us in heaven; <hi>Irgoe to prepare a place for you:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.2.</note> ſo here 'tis Chriſts work to prepare places and conditions for his people, to ſanctifie every thing to them. As on the one ſide he curſes all to his enemies, <hi>I will curſe your blesſings;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2.2.</note> there is a ſecret curſe goes along with all thoſe things they count their greateſt bleſſings: ſo on the other ſide, he bleſſes all thoſe things to his children, which they might conceive to be curſes to them and to make moſt againſt them. <hi>Iacob</hi> when he ſaw <hi>Ioſeph</hi> loſt, and <hi>Simeon</hi> left bound in Aegypt, and <hi>Benjamin</hi> to be carried from him, he ſtrait concluded, <hi>all theſe things are against mee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 42.36.</note> when yet all made for him, and preſervation of himſelfe and the life of his family in Aegypt.<note place="margin">Gen. 45.5.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> thought his own caſting into priſon would have proved his ruine for ever;<note place="margin">Gen. 39.20.</note> when yet God made it the means of his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt advancement. The Iewes thought the plot of <hi>Haman</hi> would have bin their confuſion, when yet God ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156219:12"/>it as the day intended for their deſtruction, was turned to them <hi>from ſorrow to joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heſt. 9.22.</note> 
               <hi>from mourning into a good day; Moſes</hi> notes it touching <hi>Balaams</hi> curſe, with which <hi>Balak</hi> King of Moab would have had him curſe Iſrael,<note place="margin">Deut 23.5.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord thy God turned the curſe into a blesſing to thee, becauſe the Lord thy God loved thee:</hi> if wee be ſuch as God loves, Chriſt will turne all curſings into bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, all things ſhall be bleſt to us, nothing curſt to us.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In ſettling an externall eccleſiaſticall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy: as Chriſt is King of his Church, he will have his Church governed in his own way, not according to the fancies and inventions of man. Wee muſt not deny that to Chriſt in government of his Kingdom, which wee yeild to all earthly Monarchs in the government of theirs, when Chriſt, after his reſurrection continued for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes upon earth among his diſciples, <hi>ſpeaking of the things pertaining to the Kingdom of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.3.</note> wee cannot think he would omit the giving of rules for the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the regiment of his Church. And when S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels the Elders of Epheſus, <hi>he had not ſhunned to declare to them the whole councell of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.27.</note> wee muſt take it in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of thoſe directions himſelf and the reſt of the diſciples had received from Chriſt for the government of his Church. What this frame of Church policy is, which hath bin ſo long in diſpute, and is yet <hi>ſub judice,</hi> will be more proper for a Synod then a Sermon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of. I only hint this, but leave it to that grave con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation you have already deſigned, not doubting your honourable care in haſtning that work, which muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly conduce much to the advancing and ſetling Chriſts Government more exactly among us.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2.<note place="margin">Reaſons of the point.</note> Let us conſider the reaſons why God would
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156219:12"/>have ſuch a ſolemne adminiſtration of a kingdom by Chriſt:</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reſpect of Glory that might accrew both to Chriſt the Son, and to God the father.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of Chriſt, that he might receive the honour due to his deity, which the work of humiliation might take from him; though he were the true God,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.6.</note> 
               <hi>equall with the Father;</hi> yet taking upon him the forme of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, that he might be fitted to humble himſelfe to the death of the Croſſe; this humiliation made the world, that knew him not, ſtrip him of his glory; they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted him a divell, a glutton, a malefactor, crucified him between two theeves,<note place="margin">Objiciunt nos honorem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre homini crucifixo my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterium hujus rei ignorantes, <hi>Iuſt. Mart.</hi>
               </note> put a crowne of thornes upon his head in deriſion, and ever after derided the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they beleived in a crucified God. Chriſt muſt now be repayred in his honour; therfore God appoynts him to be King of his Church, that he may be advanced in their eyes who had ſo much vilified him: <hi>the Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all judgment,</hi> that is, the diſpenſation of all government, <hi>to the Son,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>that all men ſhould honour the Son as they honour the Father:</hi> as the world vilified him as a malefactor, they might now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg him God equall with the Father, and honour him with the ſame honour, wherewith they honour the Father: greatly exalted becauſe greatly humbled, <hi>the ſtone which the builders refuſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>is made the head of the corner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In reſpect of the Father, that he might have the more glory from ſuch a ſolemn adminiſtration of a kingdom by Chriſt: as God was more glorified by giving Chriſt to be a Redeemer, by finding out ſuch a way of ſaving ſinners, where God became man, and two natures, the divine and humane united together, Chriſt taking fleſh and ſuffering, then if he had ſaved his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156219:13"/>any other way without Chriſt: ſo now, it would bring more glory to God, by exalting Chriſt as King, and giving him the ſolemn adminiſtration of a Kingdom, then if God ſhould have governed his people in the generall way, as he governs the world. <hi>God has highly exalted him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2 9, 11.</note> 
               <hi>and given him a name above every name, that every tongue ſhould confeſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt is Lord, to the glory of the Father.</hi> That's a main end, why Chriſt who was firſt humbled, was after exalted, the glory of the Father; that ſolemn adminiſtration of the Kingdom by Chriſt brings more glory to the Father.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in reſpect of Gods people; none ſo fit to be King to any people as ſuch a one, who is allyed to them, and may be the more tender of them: As God gave the precept touching a King for the Iſraelites, they muſt chooſe <hi>one from among their brethren:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17.15.</note> ſo Chriſt therefore fitteſt becauſe our brother, he took our nature upon him, and became <hi>Immanuel,</hi> God with us, God one of us, of the ſame fleſh and blood with us, tis the ſame in this, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks touching the fitneſſe of Chriſt's being made high Prieſt for us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe having taken our nature,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>and being compaſt with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities,</hi> he is likely to be the more compaſſionate to us: 'tis fitteſt Chriſt ſhould be our King, that having the ſame nature with us, and compaſt about with our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, he might exerciſe the more tenderneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, as knowing beſt our frailties and the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of our natures; a King of our brethren is fitteſt for us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In reſpect of Gods enemies and ours; the more to awe them, when they ſhall ſee him reigning over them, whom they derided; ſee him glorious in the adminiſtration of a kingdom and all power over them, who once crucified, and yet doe daily crucifie him, ſee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156219:13"/>Chriſt King of ſuch whom they perſecute; and fight for them and judge their cauſe, whom they afflict: 'tis ſaid of the wicked of the world, when they ſee the ſon of man comming in the cloudes in the day of judgment, <hi>they ſhall mourne;</hi> feare him as a terrible judge,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.30.</note> ready to take vengeance on them, who have uſed him ſo deſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: it muſt needs be the ſame here,<note place="margin">Ipſe erit judex, qui ſub judice ſtetit, ut vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant impii ejus gloriam, in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus manſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem ſaevie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. <hi>Proſp. Sent.</hi> 337.</note> though in a leſſe degree; what can more awe and terrifie wicked people, then to know, Chriſt reignes, he ſits heere as King to obſerve them, to judge them, to plague them, whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they have ſo much vilified, whoſe honour they have ſo much laid in the duſt, whoſe ſervants they have ſo perſecuted, whoſe cauſe they have ſo much oppoſed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in reſpect of a ſuitableneſſe betwixt the works of redemption and government: it were unequall Chriſt ſhould redeem us, and not govern us: unjuſt, that we ſhould ſerve any other, then him who hath laid down the ranſome for us. There is <hi>jus redemptionis</hi> in this, he who ranſoms a ſlave, ought to have his ſervice: if Chriſt while we were ſlaves of the devill, hath ranſomed us and bought us with a price, the price <hi>of his own blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1 18.</note> it is equall we ſhould ſerve him, give him the ſervice, both of our bodies and ſpirits, becauſe <hi>they are now his,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.20.</note> and no more our own. It were unequall, we ſhould expect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from him, and yet not yeeld obedience to him: that is the very end of our redemption,<note place="margin">Luke 1.72.</note> 
               <hi>that wee being delivered out of the hands of our enemies ſhould ſerve him without feare, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him all the daies of our lives.</hi> Here we ſhould take St. <hi>Peters</hi> rule to <hi>Ananias,</hi> touching the poſſeſſion he had ſold: <hi>Why haſt thou kept back part of the price, while it remained unſold, was it not thine owne?</hi> it was thine owne,<note place="margin">Acts 5.3.</note> thou mighteſt have done with it as thou pleaſedſt: but having ſold it to God, why doſt thou now keep back that which
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156219:14"/>is Gods? while we were our own, we might diſpoſe our ſelves according to our own wils; but now Chriſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bought us, what right have we to keep back from Chriſt that which is Chriſts? if we belong to God by the right of purchaſe, why ſhould we defraud God of his due? while we were Satans, we might give unto Satan the things of Satan, ſerve him whoſe we were: but now being Gods purchaſe, we ought to give unto God <hi>the things of God,</hi> ſerve him whoſe we are.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> If Chriſt bee King of his Church, let Gods people comfort themſelves in this, that Chriſt reignes, that Chriſt ſits as King among us. The uſe <hi>David</hi> makes of this doctrine,<note place="margin">Pſal. 97.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord reignes,</hi> what then? <hi>let the earth rejoyce, let the multitude of the Iſles be glad thereof.</hi> We that live here in the Iſles, have not we a portion in this joy and comfort, that we know Chriſt is King, and reignes among us; let the earth rejoyce, and the multitude of the Iſles be glad. Indeed if Gods people conſider, they are but <hi>a little flock of kids</hi> among many lions,<note place="margin">1 Kings 20, 27. Mat. 10.16. Cant. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>a few ſheep</hi> among many wolves, a ſingle <hi>lilly among many thornes:</hi> if they conſider, what machinations, what pernicious plots are daily contrived againſt them: if we had not this to ſupport us, to know Chriſt is King, that he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders all for the beſt for us, ſubdues our enemies, protects us from plots of malignant perſons, preſerves us in the midſt of greateſt dangers, it might well caſt us into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of ever holding up our heads with comfort. But when we remember that Chriſt ſits as King among us, he is above in heaven, and laughs at the plots of wicked men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord has them in deriſion:</hi> men may be buſie in contriving, but Chriſt is as buſie in defeating: here is a glorious beame of comfort breaks in upon us under this notion of Chriſts being King, his reigning in the midſt of his people. Comfortably may we apply that of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156219:14"/>Prophet, <hi>look upon Sion, the City of our ſolemnities:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 33.20.</note> 
               <hi>thine eyes ſhall ſee Ieruſalem a quiet habitation, a tabernacle that ſhall not be taken down; not one of the ſtakes thereof ſhall ever bee removed, neither ſhall any of the cords thereof bee broken: but there the glorious Lord will be to us a place of broad rivers; for the Lord is our judge, the Lord is our law giver, the Lord is our King, he will ſave us.</hi> When we look up to Chriſt, and meditate with our ſelves, is not Chriſt our judge, is not he our law-giver, is not he our King? he will ſave us; we may with comfort look upon Sion the City of our ſolemnities, and ſhall ſee our Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem againe a quiet habitation. I ſhewed you before, it is one of the prime acts of Chriſts Kingly office to preſerve his ſubjects: if we break not covenant with him, he will help us: and why ſhould we not then boldly ſay, <hi>if the Lord be our helper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>we will not feare what man can doe unto us:</hi> then we feare when we know we have many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and few helpers: but if Chriſt be our King who can help us, why ſhould we feare what man or devill, or powers of darkneſſe can do unto us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> It informs us in this, how we ſhould live one towards another, as ſubjects of the ſame King: the myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Church beares analogy with the politick body of the State: ſubjects, as they are knit under one head, ſo they ſhould be of one minde, and have one heart: and that chiefly in three particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in love, and keeping communion one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: union with Chriſt the head, will produce com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the members, <hi>we have fellowſhip one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Iohn 1.7.</note> There be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> certaine things which are common among Chriſtian friends:<note place="margin">Ariſt. Pol. l. 2. c. 3.</note> a community in goods, <hi>all that beleeved were together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.44. Ex ſubſtantia familiari fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres ſumus. <hi>Tert ap. adv. gent. c.</hi> 39.</note> 
               <hi>and had all things common:</hi> a community in counſels, contributing helps of advice upon occaſions offered: a community in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156219:15"/>the Churches in the <hi>Acts</hi> held intelligence together, and the Eccleſiaſticall ſtories tell us, at <hi>Lions</hi> in <hi>France</hi> the Saints were wont to ſend to the Saints in <hi>Phrygia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omnia apud nos indiſcreta ſunt praeter ux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores. <hi>Tert. ap. adv. gent. c.</hi> 34. Occultisſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; inſignibus noſcunt &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant mutuò penè antequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m noverint. <hi>Man.</hi> Ejuſmodi vel maximè dile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio notam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis inurit penes quoſdam, vide, inquiunt, ut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicem ſe dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. <hi>Tert ibid.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Clem. Al. paed. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ibid.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Greg. Naz. de Nonna Orat.</hi> 11.</note> concerning the affaires of the Church: all things they had common; but eſpecially a communion of converſation, a delight in the ſociety one of another. 'Twas a ſaying of a Heathen in the primitive times, what ſtrange people theſe Chriſtians are, they are as well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted in half an houre as others are in half a yeare. We want this communion among us; we keep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with any kind of people, rather then with the Saints of God. We every day ſay, we beleeve a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, but we make it in our practice rather a chymera then a thing reall; we delight not in it. O this ſtrangeneſſe and loathneſſe to ſociety with good men, it is not agreeable with that heavenly converſation Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould have. This ſhould be the ligament of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſociety, their relation to Chriſt, as they are fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Citizens of the heavenly Jeruſalem, and the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of God, and knit together under one King. Wee ſhould deſire to keep the ſame company here, we ſhall doe hereafter in heaven: there our company ſhall bee God and the Saints; ſo it ſhould be here. 'Tis true, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill commerce may be kept with all, but we ought to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh in chuſing our companions, that when we die we may only change our place, not our company: if here we enjoy the preſence of God, and ſociety of the Saints, our change will be but eaſie; when we go hence, we go but to have a nearer communion with them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in having a fellow feeling with them of their miſeries: every member of the body hath a ſenſe of the injuries the other members ſuffer. There be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain trees, whoſe leaves,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem. Al. Strom. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> if cut or toucht, the other leaves contract themſelves, and for a ſpace hang downe their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156219:15"/>heads: ſuch an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a conſent of ſpirits, as <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> cals it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Clem. ibid.</note> there ſhould be betwixt all the children of God. If the man, that is in us, be ſpirituall, that humane affection, which is in us naturally, is turned into a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affection, as being partakers of the ſame ſpirit. Tis ſaid of <hi>Hypocrates</hi> twins, they laught together, and wept together: as there will bee a rejoycing with them that rejoyce, ſo there will be a mourning with them that mourne; a contracting our ſpirits with ſorrow, a hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of the head in ſenſe of our brethrens miſeries. Twas the ſin of the people for which God threatens them, that they <hi>lay upon beds of ivory, and eat the lambs of the flock, and chanted to the ſound of the violl,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Am. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>and drank wine in bowles, and annointed themſelves with chiefe oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but were not grieved for the afflictions of Ioſeph.</hi> What nation deeper drencht in this ſin, then wee have been? we have long ſeen our brethren in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and now in <hi>Ireland</hi> wallowing in their blood. Each of thoſe Kingdoms ready to crie out with the Church, was ever ſorrow like my ſorrow? <hi>Is it nothing to you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>all ye that paſſe by? behold and ſee if there be any ſorrow like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſorrow, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me in the day of his fierce wrath.</hi> O, hath not the wrath of God gone over thoſe Countries, like waves rolling one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, billow upon billow; the famine after the ſword, and the plague after the famine? <hi>may not we tell our children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>and our children tell their children, and their children an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other generation: that which the palmer worme hath left, hath the locuſt eaten; and that which the locuſt hath left, hath the canker worme eaten; and that which the canker worme hath left, hath the caterpiller eaten:</hi> have greater judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments been recorded to poſterity, then have been exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted upon theſe nations? inſomuch as all their plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are devoured: what the ſword hath left, the famine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156219:16"/>has deſtroyed; and what the famine hath left, the plague has conſumed. Are not the judgements upon our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſuch as may well <hi>make our eares tingle to heare them?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iet. 19.3.</note> doe we not now ſee them as the afflicted Saints are deſcribed, <hi>impriſoned, ſtoned, ſawen aſunder, ſlain with the ſword,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>wandring about upon the cold mountains and deſarts naked and ſtarving, at beſt in ſheep-skins and goat-skins, deſtitute, afflicted, tormented, lying comfortleſſe in dens and caves of the earth?</hi> wives abuſed before their husbands faces, virgins deflowred, women with childe ript up, poore infants ſnacht from their mothers breaſt, and daſht againſt the ſtones: here ſome lying naked periſhing with cold, there others ſtarving with hunger? <hi>the land that was as the garden of Eden, now become a barren wilderneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel. 2.3.</note> that brings forth nothing but thorns to crown Chriſt with (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks of the land of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi>) or nothing but monſters of men, that delight to have their hands in the bowels, and bathed in the blood of the Saints of God? everywhere miſery, and all the direfull effects of the deſolations of warre? this, I ſay, have wee not long ſeen? and yet <hi>ubi viſcera,</hi> where are our bowels yearning upon theſe afflictions of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? may I not ſay,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.12.</note> in the Apoſtles words, <hi>are we not ſtraitned in our own bowels?</hi> are not our bowels ſhut up againſt our brethren? how few of us that leave off any pleaſure, or take any the leaſt time more to mourne in private for theſe afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph?</hi> are we not as wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and full of jollity and good fellowſhip as formerly, as if theſe miſeries we ſee upon others did not at all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our ſelves? they, who are not ſenſible of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of their poor brethren, 'tis a ſign they are not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the kingdom of Chriſt. Chriſt himſelf <hi>hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion upon us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2.</note> who are his members, in our miſeries: there is no affliction upon Gods people, but God is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156219:16"/>with them, <hi>in all their afflictions he was afflicted;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 63.9. Non perdit viſcera pia mater eccleſia. <hi>Aug. ho.</hi> 27. Heb. 13.3. 1 Pet. 3.8.</note> The Church our mother hath bowels of compaſſion towards her children, and ſhall we have no ſence of our brethrens miſeries, not be afflicted in their afflictions? <hi>not remember them that are in bonds as bound with them, and them which ſuffer adverſity, as being alſo in the body? Bee all of one mind, ſaies the Apoſtle, having compaſsion one of another, love as brethren, be pittifull:</hi> If we love as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, we ſhall have theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, theſe bowels of compaſſion and pitty one towards another, when it is well with them we ſhall rejoyce, as the people of <hi>Roma</hi> did for <hi>Germanicus,</hi> when they heard he was recovered, they went about ſinging, The City is ſafe, our Country ſafe, becauſe <hi>Germanicus</hi> is ſafe: Then we ſhall rejoyce and ſing, Our City, our Country, our perſons,<note place="margin">Salva Roma, Salva patria, ſalvus eſt Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicus.</note> we are all in a happy condition, when our brethren and our Religion and the Church of God is in peace, but till that be done, till God make our Ieruſalem a quiet habitation, till God lift up the heads of our brethren againe, and give the Goſpel a free progreſſe againe, and make Religion flouriſh again, and ſet up the Kingdome of Chriſt and his Ordinances againe in their beauty and power and purity, in other Nations as well as our owne, we muſt mourne with them that mourne, and weep with them that weep, and be afflicted in the afflictions of Gods people, if wee be not, it is a ſigne wee are not members of the ſame body, nor Subjects of the ſame King.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In relieving their cauſes and perſons with the ſtrength of their owne perſons and ſubſtance: brethren and fellow-ſubjects muſt contribute to the reliefe and deliverance of thoſe who are of the ſame bloud, and of the ſame profeſſion with themſelves: <hi>Wee muſt doe here,</hi> as <hi>Ieſſe</hi> ſaid to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.18.</note> Goe look how thy Brethren
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156219:17"/>fare: Wee ſhould be alwayes eying <hi>our Brethren,</hi> the people of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 41.1.</note> to ſee how they fare, <hi>conſider the poore,</hi> as the Pſalmiſts expreſſion is, that we may relieve them in their diſtreſſes.<note place="margin">Gen. 14.14.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> ventured his owne perſon and all his Family, for the redemption of his Brother <hi>Lot. Saul and all the Iſraelites hazarded themſelves</hi> for their fellowes; <hi>the Inhabitants of Iabes Gilead:</hi> In the time of perſecution,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 11.8.</note> the Diſciples, <hi>every man according to his ability ſent reliefe unto their Brethren which dwelt in Iudaea:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 11.29.</note> Nay, the Macedonians went in this <hi>beyond their ability,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3.</note> more then their eſtates would beare; and they that were of the ſame faith, all that beleeved <hi>ſold their poſſeſsions for the ſupply of the needs of the reſt of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.44.</note> and ſuch contributions they uſed to make in thoſe dayes, <hi>that every man had ſufficient, neither was any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that lacked, for as many as were in poſſeſsion of Lands and houſes, ſold them, and brought the prices, and laid them downe at the Apoſtles feet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.34.</note> 
               <hi>and distribution was made to every man according as he had need.</hi> 'Tis not enough to ſay, wee are all ſubjects of Chriſts Kingdome in words, but we muſt ſhew it in deeds; otherwiſe it is but as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeakes, a vaine expreſſion, to ſay to one that is naked and deſtitute of food, <hi>Depart in peace. bee warmed and be filled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>and yet not give them thoſe things that are needfull for them:</hi> If we ſerve Chriſt, wee muſt love him; if we love Chriſt, then as he laid downe his life for us, ſo muſt wee be content upon a neceſſity to lay downe our lives for the Brethren; <hi>But much more then, whoſo hath this worlds goods and ſees his brother hath need and ſhuts up his bowels of compaſsion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.16.</note> 'Twill be a ſad evidence againſt us in the day of Judgement if we neither <hi>feed the hungry nor cloath the naked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.43.</note> and tis a terrible threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>hee ſhall have judgement without mercy who ſhewes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156219:17"/>no mercy.</hi> Doe not delude thy ſoule,<note place="margin">— Divitias diſpergendo pauperibus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecerunt, &amp; talimodo in coeleſtibus the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauros tutius condiderunt Aug. prob. ep. 121.</note> in accounting thy ſelfe a member of Chriſts body, a Subject of Chriſts Kingdome, and yet ſee another member, another Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject periſh before thine eyes and not relieve him, but ſhutſt up thy bowels of compaſſion againſt him. <hi>Clemens</hi> tells us of the Elephants, if one fall into a Ditch and cryes out, the next that heares him preſently gathers all the Heard and help him out: If any poore brother be in diſtreſſe and cannot relieve himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Strom.</hi> l. 1. Cyprianus Chriſtianus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus omnem ſubſtantiam ſuam pauperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus erogavit. Hier.</note> the whole So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety muſt doe it. Great are the exigences of our poor Brethren at this time in <hi>Ireland,</hi> there is Chriſt naked, and Chriſt hungry, and Chriſt in priſon, and Chriſt ficke, Chriſt in his poor Subjects: Let us cloath Chriſt and feed Chriſt,<note place="margin">— Reponam hunc theſauru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> univerſum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud creatorem liberis autem meis relinqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſaurum ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum creatorem quod cùm dix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet, erogavit omnia paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus. Druſ. Haeb. Apo. Mat. 21.3.</note> and redeeme Chriſt out of the hands of his enemies. Let us not now looke upon our Cold with a covetous eye, nor keep it with a griping hand, nor be nice of our perſons, when Chriſt hath need of us and our wealth, as Chriſt ſaid, when he ſent for the Aſſe, ſay, <hi>The Lord hath need of him, and they will let him goe:</hi> When the Lord hath need of our perſons, and need of our purſes, let us let them goe, be free in the cauſes of Chriſt; we are not his Subjects, if we helpe not him nor our fellow-ſubjects. I know I ſhall eaſily have a pardon from you (Honourable and Beloved) if I be an earneſt Advocate in theſe cauſes of Chriſt, for which you have ſhewed your ſelves already ſo faithfull and zealous, the Lord reward you for your care; but give me leave onely to put you in remembrance of this, as the Viſion appeared to Saint <hi>Paul, There ſtood a man of Macedonia and prayed him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 16.9.</note> 
               <hi>come over into Macedonia and helpe us:</hi> Chriſt hath long appeared to you, and called for your help for <hi>Ireland;</hi> the Lord, I ſay, will reward you for what helpe you have already afforded them: but I beſeech you, let every Faſt day wee keepe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156219:18"/>for them put you in mind of their preſſing miſeries and their bleeding condition, which now begins againe to be deſperate; Let mee ſay to you in the words of the men of <hi>Gibeon</hi> to <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 10.6.</note> 
               <hi>Slacke not thy hand from thy ſervants, come up to us quickly and ſavt us and helpe us.</hi> As <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeakes of a word fitly ſpoken or ſpoken in ſeaſon,<note place="margin">Prov. 25.11.</note> it is a word upon its wheeles, as the Originall inforces: ſo it is with a worke, a worke done in ſeaſon, it is a worke upon its wheeles, an excellent worke, that goes on to purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> If Chriſt be our King, let me then ſtirre you up in a word of exhortation, to performe the duty of good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects unto Chriſt, to helpe Chriſt into his Throne and maintaine him there, and that partly in reſpect of our ſelves, partly in reſpect of others.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of our ſelves, to Crowne Chriſt in our owne hearts, to ſet up his Kingdome within our ſelves the Kingdome of God is within you, to ſet it up in our hearts; we eaſily deſire Chriſt a Saviour to ſave us, but not a King to governe us: Wee are ready to cry out with the Diſciples,<note place="margin">Mat. 14.30.</note> 
               <hi>Lord ſave us, we periſh;</hi> but as ready againe to ſay with the wicked Citizens,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.14.</note> 
               <hi>We will not have this man to reigne over us.</hi> Alas, wee muſt not expect Chriſt ſhould be a Saviour, unleſſe he be received as a King, as <hi>Iephtah</hi> anſwered the Elders of <hi>Gilead, Why come you to me now when you are in diſtreſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 21.7.9.</note> 
               <hi>if the Lord deliver your enemies before me, ſhall I be your head?</hi> Wee muſt not fly to Chriſt onely in the time of our diſtreſſe, when our ſinnes preſſe us, and we ſee the mouth of Hell open to ſwallow us up, unleſſe withall, when Chriſt hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from our ſpirituall enemies, wee be contented to take him for our head, for our Lord to rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne us as well as for our Saviour to ſave us: O let us crowue Chriſt in our hearts: not doe as the Jewes did,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156219:18"/>ſet <hi>a crowne of thornes</hi> upon his head, but ſet a Crowne of Gold upon his head, a Crown of Soveraigntie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him our Lord and King, feare and obey him: Crowne him as <hi>Iehoiada</hi> and the people crowned King <hi>Ioaſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 11.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>they crowned him and compaſt him about with their ſwords in their hands,</hi> ready to fight againſt all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: Set up Chriſt in the throne of thy heart and hold thy ſword in thy hand to fight againſt all Chriſts enemies, all thy own luſts, thy rebelling affections that fight againſt Chriſt the King of thy ſoule.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To help to advance Chriſts Kingdome in others, to helpe to lift up Chriſt and to ſet up his Scepter over all the World. God has promiſed to give Chriſt the Nations for his inheritance, and the uttetmoſt parts of the Earth for his poſſeſſion: 'tis a great work to bring people into Chriſt, to ſet up his Kingdome, ſo as Chriſt may come to inherit the Nations, and to poſſeſſe the uttermoſt parts of the Earth, every one muſt come in to help in this worke. When the Tabernacle was to bee made, every one that was of a willing heart brought his offering, <hi>ſome gold, ſome braſſe, ſome ſcarlet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 35.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſome Goates hayre;</hi> every man according to his ability. When the Temple was to be built, every one ſet to his helping hand, <hi>Salomon</hi> prepared gold, <hi>Hyram</hi> ſent Cedar Trees, ſome were hewers in the mountaines, ſome bearers of burthens, every one contributed according to his qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; it muſt be ſo here in the advancing of Chriſts Kingdome, 'tis the great worke God hath deſigned us for, every one muſt ſet to his helping hand according to his ability, and the meanes and opportunities God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to him. Chriſt is King, yet hee hath many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies labour to keep him out of his Throne: 'tis our part to helpe him in.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is ill handled by enemies at home in private
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156219:19"/>contriving plots againſt him:<note place="margin">Act. 5.39.</note> O for ſome <hi>Gamaliels</hi> to give ſeaſonable counſell to take men off from plotting againſt Chriſt. He is worſe handled by enemies abroad in publike, there he is not onely plotted againſt, but already upon the Croſſe, looke into <hi>Germany,</hi> looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ireland;</hi> we may eaſily with <hi>Thomas</hi> beleeve him to be there, we may ſee the print of his nayles in his hands and in his feete, and may put our fingers into thoſe ghaſtly wounds are already made in his body and his Members:<note place="margin">Mat. 27.59.</note> O for ſome <hi>Ioſephs</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> to take him downe from the Croſſe. All perſons are called in to this worke, People, Miniſters, Magiſtrates, Kings themſelves: As they are Monarchs, they are offended if any thing be done againſt Monarchy; let them bee carefull of Chriſts Monarchy, he is King of Kings, they are all called in to ſerve Chriſt in this Pſalme.<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave (Honourable and Beloved) to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you in a few words three Kingdomes which are maine impediments to the advancement of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſts, the Kingdome of ſin, the Kingdome of Satan, and the Kingdome of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The Kingdome of ſin: Sin is a King, <hi>Let not ſinne reigne in your mortall bodies:</hi> Let it not play the King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, beware of ſuffering any ſin to be countenanced among us, ſuffer not ſin to be enacted by any Law nor to receive countenance from miſconſtruction of Lawes; ſinnes may bee committed in ſecret and none can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them; but it will lye upon the Magiſtrates, when publike avouched ſinnes are not ſet againſt: Idolatry was wont to be in corners and by ſtealth; how open of late in <hi>England,</hi> how much juſtified by many, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things pleaded for it? how tollerated in <hi>Ireland,</hi> even to the deſtruction of that poore land? how, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like drunkenneſſe and uncleanneſſe? in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:156219:19"/>time: <hi>they that were drunke, were drunke in the night:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.7.</note> that was the modeſty of thoſe times, though they went on in a courſe of ſinne, they choſe darkneſſe to cover their ſinnes: <hi>It is a ſhame to ſpeake of thoſe things which are done of them in ſecret,</hi> ſhamefull things,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> but yet done in ſecret. How ſhameleſſe are people in theſe dayes? how are all principles of common modeſty, as well as common honeſty extinguiſht in them? that they commit ſinne in the very face of the Sunne, and bluſh not: a ſhameleſſe generation, <hi>that declare their ſinnes as Sodom and hide them not:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 3.9.</note> a deſperate and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſtate of people, that are not onely paſt feare and ſorrow, but alſo paſt ſhame.<note place="margin">Ier. 8.i3.</note> Set againſt this Kingdom of ſinne; if Lawes be wanting, let them be made; if made ſee to the execution; let not ſinne reigne among us ſo open, ſo uncontrouled: publike ſinnes are in the way of a judgement from God: 'Twas a judgement upon <hi>David</hi> and his houſe, <hi>that his wives ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in the face of the Sun;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Hoſ. 4.17.</note> and that <hi>Ephraim ſhould go after idols and be let alone in their idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are three things worthy the conſideration, how they may be ſuppreſt. 1. The <hi>bacchanalia,</hi> that numerous iſſue of Taverns, and Ale-houſes, ſo infinitely degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their firſt inſtitution; that they are become the neſts and harbourers of all ſin and diſorder. 2. The <hi>lupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria,</hi> houſes of uncleanneſſe, cages of uncleane birds. 3. The <hi>theatra,</hi> theaters and ſtages, where profanneſſe and vice is thought to be indeed ſatyrically whipt and preſented, that it might be hated; but is rather ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonated and acted, as people become more in love with it. Tis true, it will be hard to finde out waies of ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing theſe publick places of drunkenneſſe, uncleanneſſe, profanneſſe, which are indeed the ſeminaries and nurſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of all diſorders, and the bane of the Church and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156219:20"/>Common-wealth: Yet certainly, there may be a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reformation wrought: let them have a place in your thoughts in due time: theſe are mighty enemies to Chriſts Kingdom, and Miniſters finde unſpeakable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments to the progreſſe of religion and the courſe of their miniſtry from theſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.12.</note> the kingdom of Satan: Satan is a king, he is <hi>the ruler of the darknes of this world:</hi> that labours to keep all under a ſpiritual Aegyptian darknes, that labours to blind the minds of people, <hi>in whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds of thoſe that beleeve not:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4.</note> 'tis a mighty policy of Satans againſt Chriſts Kingdome, to labour, that people may be kept in ignorance, that dumb dogs may be ſet up that will never open their mouths to teach knowledge: and that the means may be kept from the Church, that ſo worthy men may not be brought in, who conſider, <hi>the Labourer is worthy of his hire.</hi> Looke to this, when time ſhall be, ſee that there be a candle in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry candleſtick that is able to give light, a paſtor in every flock that is able to feed: and let there be ſuch encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements as may enable men to go on comfortably and chearfully in the work: there hath been already much ſaid in this argument by others; I ſhall not need to ſay more in it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the kingdom of Antichriſt: he is a King, nay a God, <hi>who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelfe above all that is called God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.4</note> 
               <hi>ſo as he as God ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf that he is God:</hi> the oppoſitions Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom receives from Popery, are notorious to all: as there was a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 6. ſomething that was an obſtacle, <hi>that hindered the full revelation of the working of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of iniquity</hi> in the Apoſtles dayes, the Kingdom of the Emperours hindering the advancement of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Antichriſt: ſo now Popery, that is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:156219:20"/>high and ſpreading power of the kingdom of Antichriſt is a mighty impediment to the enlargement of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt. The way then to ſet up Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is to pull downe Antichriſts: there is a promiſe, that Chriſts ſhall ſtand for ever, but Antichriſts ſhall have a fall; and that the raiſing of Chriſts to its higheſt pitch, ſhall be by the ruines of Antichriſts. After the prophecy of the <hi>fall of the whore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 18. Rev. 19. Rev. 20.</note> and <hi>the deſtruction of the beaſt,</hi> followes the deſcription of the glorious Kingdom of Chriſt. It is with thoſe two Kingdoms, as with the ſcales in the ballance, when the one goes down, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther goes up: or as it was with the houſes of <hi>Saul</hi> &amp; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, the houſe of Saul waxed weaker and weaker,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>but the houſe of David ſtronger and ſtronger:</hi> the Kingdom of Chriſt goes up by Antichriſts going down; that waxeth ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſtronger, as this waxeth weaker and weaker. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware then of the connivence at Popery, tollerations of Idolatry, falſe worſhip, downe with theſe, caſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt out of his ſaddle, wherein he has ſate too faſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, that Chriſt may better get up into his Stirrup, to ride about conquering his enemies: And let all you doe in theſe particulars, be done.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With faithfull reſolutions to lay downe all your own ends and intereſts, and to ſeek Gods glory: 'twas the Apoſtles complaint, <hi>All men ſeeke their owne things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>but no man the things of Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> So tis ſtill, we more ſeeke our owne things then thoſe that belong to Chriſt and his Kingdome, this ſhould be the maine aime of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of us, whatſoever falls to our ſelves, to looke to this, to doe our duty to Chriſt; if that be not propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed firſt as our main end, we ſhall never proſecute it cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially, they are the prime principles of Chriſtianity, <hi>to deny our ſelves and take up the Croſſe and follow Chriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 8.34.</note> If theſe things be not firſt reſolved on, to lay downe our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:156219:21"/>ſelves, and to be contented with Chriſts Croſſe, and Chriſts yoake, and that forme of Chriſts government, which he has ſet downe in his Word, and not what our ſelves fancie, and to ſuffer what he will have us, and to follow him whether he will carry us, we ſhall doe little for the ſetting up of his kingdome, while our thoughts are turn'd wholly on our ſelvs and our own intereſts and raiſing our owne fortunes, wee eaſily forget Chriſt and fetting up his Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With zeale to God;<note place="margin">Ratione rerum agendum eſt, non libidine, Salv. de gub. Rescu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa cum cauſa, ratio cum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione confli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, Aug. de util. cred. In cauſa religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis, nobis ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ex arbitrio noſtro indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere licet, ſed nec eligere q od aliquis ex arbi rio ſuo in duxerit. <hi>Teri.</hi>
               </note> not to do things in a formall way only, as willing to comply with the greater and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding part &amp; ſwim with the ſtream, &amp; go with the crowd; but to doe every thing you doe out of love and zeale to the cauſe you take in hand as being Gods cauſe. When you goe about to reforme the Houſe of God, to doe it, not becauſe you are offended with this or that, or this or that pleaſes your humour better, but becauſe God is offended with it, or God is pleaſed with it, that you may ſay truly, as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> both ſpake, <hi>The zeale of thy houſe hath eaten me up;</hi> not my owne humour, but zeale to Gods glory, and the glory of Gods Houſe, that there is in the heart a<note n="*" place="margin">Ignis quidam flagran aſſimi amoris, <hi>Aug.</hi> Rom. 12.11. Nen me d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Deus ſi ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil fing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſi of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io ducor, ſi veritatem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, ſi amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, ſi multum metuo ni fallor. <hi>Aug de util. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red.</hi>
               </note> fire of burning love kindled and flaming in you to God and his cauſe: When you goe on in any other ſervice to God, to doe it with fervencie, <hi>Be fervent in the ſpirit, ſerving the Lord:</hi> that will go tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row with the work, God will not forſake you in it, when done, not out of formality, but out of zeale and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to Gods cauſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. With unity of affections, as minding the ſame thing; nothing more hinders the advancement of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kingdome and Cauſes, then diviſions among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: The wicked unite themſelves ſtrongly againſt Chriſt, <hi>Gebal and Ammon, and Amaleck againſt Iſrael; Herod and Pontius Pilate</hi> made <hi>friends,</hi> that they might
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:156219:21"/>oppoſe Chriſt: <hi>The multitudes,</hi> all againſt the Apoſtles; the Princes ſet themſelves and take counſell together <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord and his anointed;</hi> they unite themſelves that there may bee no peace to Gods Church.<note place="margin">Vnitatem pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curant, ne pax ſit.</note> How ſhould Gods people unite themſelves for Chriſt, and goe on as the Iſraelites did to revenge the ſin of the <hi>Benjamites, Knit together as one man;</hi> as we pretend to have the ſame head,<note place="margin">Iudges 20.11.</note> and the ſame cauſes, ſo we ſhould have the ſame heart and the ſame ends. <hi>A Kingdome divided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand;</hi> if the Subjects of Chriſts Kingdome be divided, 'tis the way to ruine the cauſe and pull downe the Kingdome. All the Citizens of the heavenly Jeruſalem ſhould be like the Citizens of an earthly City, that is, compacted within it ſelfe, <hi>Ieruſalem is a City compacted within it ſelfe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3.</note> ſtand cloſe to one another in honeſt cauſes:<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1. Gen. 45.24. Exod. 2.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Acts 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>'Tis pleaſant for brethren to dwell together in unity; Brethren muſt not fall out by the way; Fellowes muſt not be at variance:</hi> The Spirit of God deſcended upon the Diſciples, <hi>when they were with one accord together in one place.</hi> Peace among our ſelves is a means to advance righteouſneſſe in the world, there is a ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of theſe noted in Scripture, <hi>Righteouſnes and Peace have kiſſed each other; follow peace and holineſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10. Heb. 12.14. Heb. 7.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ciem Al. Str. l.</hi> 5</note> Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>King of Righteouſneſſe and King of peace,</hi> as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Numa,</hi> he erected a Temple of Faith and peace; peace among your ſelves will be a meane the better to advance faith and holineſſe in the Church. If we would doe great things for Chriſt, we muſt be <hi>like-minded, of one accord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>of one minde;</hi> as diviſion is a work of the fleſh, <hi>while one ſayes I am of Paul; another, I am of Apollos, are ye not carnall?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3. Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdia res parvae creſeunt diſcordia mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae dilabuntur. Gen. 15.10, 11. Pſal. 80.6.</note> ſo it layes us open to great inconveniences; diſcord drawes ruine upon great undertakings; <hi>the ravenous birds came downe upon Abrahams Sacrifices, when divided. Priam</hi> and his ſonnes laught at the diviſions of the <hi>Grecians, Thou makeſt us a ſtrife unto our Neighbours, and our enemies laugh among themſelves.</hi> Single Chriſtians may doe ſomething
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:156219:22"/>towards the diſcharge of their duty to God: but there is no noble enterprize to be waded thorow, ſo as to doe any great matter for the ſetting up Chriſts kingdome in the midſt of ſo great enemies, and ſo great oppoſitions, if it be not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken with united ſtrengths of many.</p>
            <p>To cloſe this point, I ſhall adde ſome few meditations as ſtrong allectives to draw you up, both to crowne Chriſt in your owne hearts and to help to ſet up the Kingdome of Chriſt abroad in the world.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The honourableneſſe of this ſubjection to Chriſt; there is no ſervice to the ſervice of a King; what then to him, who is King of Kings? but further, God will make it an honourable ſervice by ſtamping a ſpeciall honour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, who in ſerving God, honour him; <hi>Them that honour me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>I will honour,</hi> 'tis a word out of the mouth of God; <hi>if any man ſerve me, him will my Father honour,</hi> 'tis a word out of the mouth of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.26.</note> And if you put the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> put to <hi>Haman, What ſhall be done to the man whom the King will honour?</hi> What ſhall the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour be wherewith Chriſt will honour thoſe that be his ſubjects?<note place="margin">Rev. 1 6 Ma. 25. Rev. 2.10.</note> the Scriptures tells us, <hi>he will make us Kings, and there is a Kingdome provided for them and a Crowne to be ſet on their heads.</hi> What ſubject has ſuch a Lord? Kings doe much for their Servants, but they never ſet a Crowne up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their heads: <hi>Pharoah</hi> made <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the greateſt in the Kingdome, <hi>according to thy word ſhall all the people be ruled;</hi> yet he reſerved the Soveraignty to himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ben 41.10.</note> 
               <hi>in the Throne I will be greater then thou:</hi> but Chriſt caſts his owne Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon us, makes us Kings, not to reigne for a yeere, or a day, but to reigne with him for ever and ever: Let the force of this motive be that which <hi>Balak</hi> put to <hi>Balaam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22.5.</note> 
               <hi>let nothing hinder thee from comming to me, for I will promote thee to very great honour:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 22.16.</note> Let nothing keep us from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in to Chriſt, for hee will promote with very great honor all thoſe who come into this ſubjection, to become ſervants of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:156219:22"/>
            <p n="2">2. The profitablenes of this ſubjection;<note place="margin">Iob. 21.15.</note> 'twas the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane queſtion of wicked perſons, <hi>What is the Almighty that we ſhould ſerve him, and what profit ſhall we have if wee pray unto him?</hi> And the wicked concluſion of a rebellious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>It is vaine to ſerve God, and there is no profit that we have kept his ordinances.</hi> Gods people know,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.14.</note> there is no ſuch ſervice as the ſervice of Chriſt, no ſuch promiſes,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> no ſuch gaine as in godlineſſe, <hi>Godlineſſe is great gain, and hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of this life and of that to come:</hi> If ever wee expect things by promiſe from God, ſo as to have a bleſſing in them and not a curſe, we muſt ſerve Chriſt in the wayes of godlineſſe, that has the promiſe of this life as well as of that to come. All bleſſings come, where Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome comes;<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Firſt ſeeke Gods Kingdome and his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all other things ſhall be added to you:</hi> they ſhall be caſt in as an overplus to the bargaine; <hi>Behold, my ſervants ſhall eat, but ye ſhall be hungry; my ſervants ſhall drink, but ye ſhall be thirſty; my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but ye ſhall be aſhamed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 65.13.</note> 
               <hi>my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but yee ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and howle for vexation of ſpirit.</hi> Thats the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence Gods Servants have above Gods enemies, they have a greater portion of outward bleſſings even in this life, onely where God for ſome particular reaſons ſees fit to alter the courſe of his ordinary diſpenſations.</p>
            <p>But then further in the life to come, he that is the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of Chriſt, receives not only the advantage of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice here, but withall a glorious reward of it hereafter, <hi>hee who hath his fruit unto holineſſe, ſhall have his end ever laſting life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Let the force of this motive be that which <hi>Abner</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> why they ſhould crowne <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and receive him for their King, <hi>becauſe the Lord hath ſpoken of David, ſaying, by the hand of my ſervant David I will ſave my people Iſrael out of the hands of the Philistines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>and out of the hands of all their enemies:</hi> So here, crowne
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:156219:23"/>Chriſt in thy heart, receive him as thy King, labour to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Kingdome among others, becauſe God hath ſaid by him hee will ſave thee and all the Iſrael of God from their ſins, from the Devill, from hell. Set a crowne upon Chriſts head here in thy heart, he will crowne thee with all temporall bleſſings in this life, and ſet a crown of glory, a crown of immortality on thy head in the life to come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The neceſſity of this ſubjection to Chriſt, and of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in to the work of advancing Chriſts Kingdom in the world, in caſe we would not be miſerable in this life and that to come.</p>
            <p>No bleſſing upon a Land where Religion and Chriſts Kingdome flouriſh not; 'twas when <hi>Obed Edom</hi> entertained the Arke of God,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>that God blest him and all his houſe.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is the mother of all bleſſings, like the Heavens, it has an influence upon all things here below; it bindes all bleſſings together, as it is ſaid of <hi>Minerva's</hi> Buckler made by <hi>Phydias,</hi> he wrought it ſo artificially, that having ſet his owne name in the midſt of it, it could never be taken out, without breaking the whole frame: All bleſſings are bound up in Religion and the Goſpel and Chriſts go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment among us: if you take away theſe, you break the whole frame of bleſſings: If the <hi>Palladium</hi> be once loſt, <hi>Troy</hi> is loſt: ſteale away Chriſt and the Goſpel and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from us, we are loſt and all bleſſings loſt: Without that we ſhall have a curſe in all we enjoy, <hi>I will curſe your bleſsings:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2.2.</note> God curſes thoſe things to us, which we enjoy not in the bleſſing of the Goſpel. <hi>Woe to them,</hi> ſayes God, <hi>when I depart from them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.12.</note> If ever Chriſt depart from us, 'twill be woe to us. When the Arke of Gods preſence was taken from the Iſraelites, then <hi>Ichabod, the glory of Iſrael de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted:</hi> The Arke of Gods preſence,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.22.</note> his preſence in his ordinances, in the Goſpel, if that be taken from us, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry departs from <hi>England,</hi> no more glory, no more bleſſing. 'Tis the reaſon of the diſſolution of States and Kingdomes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:156219:23"/>Religion firſt fals, before the Common-wealth fals. The Kingdom of <hi>Iudah</hi> laſted longer then the Kingdom of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> becauſe Religion and the worſhip of God was more carefully preſerved there.<note place="margin">2 Chro. 26.2.</note> 
               <hi>When the meſſengers of God were mockt, and his words deſpiſed, and his Prophets miſuſed;</hi> that is, when Religion was wholly decayed, and Gods Kingdom of grace caſt down; then God brought a deſolation upon the State. The four Monarchies in <hi>Nebuchadnezars</hi> viſion were all to have a fall, becauſe they had nothing of Chriſts Kingdom in them. There is a neceſſity for Kingdoms to be ſubject to the Kingdom of Chriſt in reſpect of happineſſe in this life.</p>
            <p>But further, a neceſſity for all in reſpect of the life to come: unleſſe we be Chriſts ſubjects, we muſt be Chriſts enemies, and ſo ſhall be miſerable everlaſtingly; <hi>bring theſe mine enemies and ſlay them before me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 19 27.</note> God will ſlay ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly thoſe that are his enemies and will not be his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. <hi>The nation &amp; kingdom that wil not ſerve thee ſhal periſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 60.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, if we could eſcape Chriſts wrath, it were not ſo much, if we did not come under his yoke. But who ſhall eſcape his wrath, that lives not under his law?<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>Can thy heart endure, or thy hands be ſtrong, ſaith the Lord, in the day that I ſhall deale with thee?</hi> if Chriſt come to deale with us in wrath, as with his enemies, whoſe hands can be ſo ſtrong as to grapple with Chriſt? <hi>what will ye do in the day of viſitation and in the deſolation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>which ſhall come from farre, to whom will ye flie for help, and where will ye leave your glory?</hi> If Chriſt look upon us as enemies, who can protect us, what ſhall become of all our glories, what good will they doe us in the laſt day?</p>
            <p>Think upon this, you that feare not God, you that have not yet taken Chriſt for your King: if thou wilt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him now to rule in thee, he will, whether thou wilt or not, rule over thee: and which is beſt, to chuſe a King vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, that will rule thee in love, protect thee, bleſſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:156219:24"/>thee, crowne thee in heaven; or to have a King ſerve to thee againſt thy will, that will rule thee in wrath, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thee. Certainly, ſuch a one will Chriſt be unto thee, if we ſuffer him not to rule us <hi>with a golden Scepter,</hi> he will break us <hi>with an iron rod.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 19.15.</note> Let this work upon us to take <hi>Davids</hi> advice, he was a King himſelfe, and yet a ſubject of Chriſts; Chriſt was <hi>Davids</hi> ſon, and yet he was <hi>Davids</hi> King: <hi>Be wiſe now therefore, O Kings, be inſtructed ye Iudges of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.1.</note> 
               <hi>ſerve the Lord with feare and rejoyce with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling; kiſſe the ſon, leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way when his wrath is kindled but a little: bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.10, 11, 12</note> This is true wiſdom, if Chriſt will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour us, bleſſe us, ſave us in caſe we ſerve him, and certainly deſtroy us in caſe we ſerve him not: then ſerve the Lord with feare, kiſſe the ſon leſt he be angry, and ye periſh in the way: when his wrath is kindled but a little, they ſhall finde a bleſſedneſſe who ſerve him and put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> The Kingdome of Chriſt ſhall over-top the plots of wicked men, and be eſtabliſht firmly, notwithſtanding all their oppoſitions. There are two things God uſually does for this end. 1. He prevents the oppoſitions, that they ſhall not take effect. or, 2. Though plots may take the effect intended, yet God ſo turnes them, that out of them ſhall ſpring the advancement of Chriſts Kingdom. See it in the particulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in the Kingdome of grace within the hearts of Gods people: as temptations are the devils great batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, whereby he labours to overthrow our graces; ſo God makes thoſe temptations the meanes of improving and perfecting our graces.<note place="margin">Rev. 3.10.</note> God not only <hi>keeps from the houre of temptation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>and in the houre of temptation,</hi> but makes temptations the improvers of grace. <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> by their trials, and their fals had an improvement in their faith, and repentance, and love, and obedience, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:156219:24"/>their other graces. It is a generall rule for all trials, by temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as well as affliction, when Gods children are tried,<note place="margin">Iob. 23.10.</note> 
               <hi>they come forth like gold,</hi> more glorious and beautiful in their graces, and more fit for the ſervice of their Maſter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the Goſpel and Gods truths: <hi>a great and effectuall door was opened to S.</hi> Paul <hi>in preaching the Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.9.</note> 
               <hi>though there were many adverſaries.</hi> The Goſpel is <hi>the rod of Chriſts ſtrength ſent out of Sion;</hi> ſuch a ſtrength as whereby his government ſhall be ſet up in the midſt of his enimies: <hi>we can do nothing againſt the truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.2.</note> 
               <hi>but for the truth,</hi> ſeems to be a ſtrange paradox:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.8.</note> not that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a man may not oppoſe Gods truths, many do; but that no oppoſition ſhall prevaile, ſo as to deſtroy it:<note place="margin">Iſ. 40.8.</note> 
               <hi>the graſſe withereth, the flower fadeth, but the word of our God ſhall ſtand for ever.</hi> Obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it may be for a time, like the Sun under a cloud; but it wil in the end break out again, and ſhine the brighter.<note place="margin">Multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitate depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergits Cic.</note> If the devil raiſe up a <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> a falſ Prophet, to puſh at truth <hi>with horns of iron;</hi> God will raiſe up a <hi>Micaiah,</hi> a true Prophet, to maintaine it: if the devill raiſe up an <hi>Elymas, a ſorcerer, to pervert the good wayes of God,</hi> God will raiſe a <hi>Paul,</hi> a true Apoſtle, to ſtand up in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of them: if the devill raiſe up <hi>Arius,</hi> and <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius,</hi> &amp; other Hereticks, to deſtroy truths; God will raiſe up his <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> &amp; other godly champions for the clearing of them. Popery, and Arminianiſm, and Socinianiſme may now overſpread the world for a time, as Arianiſme once did in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> days, when his complaint was, that the whole world was become Arian:<note place="margin">Re. 13.3.</note> ſo now the <hi>world may wonder for a time after the beaſt, and worſhip the beaſt;</hi> yet if they be not of God, as no errours are, according to <hi>Gamaliels</hi> argument,<note place="margin">Act. 5.39.</note> 
               <hi>they will not ſtand:</hi> errours will be, like a miſt, in time diſpelled, and the Sun of truth ſtand firme in the firmament of Gods Church. How oft hath the Goſpel enlarged it ſelf by oppoſitions? the Rulers forbidding the Apoſtles to preach, <hi>made them more bold:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.29. Act. 8.4.</note> and the diſperſion of the Diſciples ſpread the Goſpel, <hi>they that were ſcattered abroad went everywhere preaching the word.</hi> The three childrens caſting into the fiery furnace brought forth that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>decree for the worſhip of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.29.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:156219:25"/>
            <p>Thirdly, in Gods people: the ſtate of the Church is indeed various,<note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is iuae, Ep 209</note> like the Moon, ſometimes in the full, ſometimes in the wane, ofttimes in the change. The Church, ſaies S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> is here in her pilgrimage, and is therefore the more obſcure. If at ſomtimes ſhe ſeem glorious, as ſhe receives influence and light from Chriſt the Sun; as the Moon, the fuller the Sun ſhines upon her, the brighter ſhe is; the more the Sun is turned from her, the darker ſhe is; yet at other times ſhe has many obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. But though ſhe may have leſſe glory, ſhe ſhall never be wholly deſtroied.<note place="margin">Mat. 7.25.</note> The Church is <hi>the houſe founded upon the rock, when the winds blow, and the floods deſcend, it ſhall ſtand, it ſhall not fall:</hi> &amp; as founded upon a rock, ſo upon the rock of rocks, Chriſt himſelf;<note place="margin">Mat. 16 18.</note> 
               <hi>upon this rock will I build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall never prevaile againſt her.</hi> Shake her they may, and give her a wound in ſome of her members, as now the Church bleeds at one veine in <hi>Germany</hi> at another in <hi>Ireland,</hi> at ſeverall veines in ſeverall parts of the world;<note place="margin">As Pheti us notes touching the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnis caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Baſil by Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſt orgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Re. 11.11.</note> yet ſhe ſhall lift up her head again, and ſhall be healed in her wounds, <hi>and like the two witneſſes ſlain in the ſtreets, after a time ſhe ſhall live again, the ſpirit of life from God ſhal enter into her, and great fear ſhall fal upon them that ſee her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſee it in Gods cauſe: whatever is undertaken in Gods cauſe, though ſometime it may ſeem to faile in particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the cauſe of the poor in perverting of judgement, the cauſe of religion by the inſolence of perſecutors and tyrants, yet in other reſpects it does certainly prevaile.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a retribution of vengeance upon the heads of thoſe, that ſet to overthrow the cauſe of God: <hi>Abel</hi> periſhed in Gods cauſe: and yet even in the death of <hi>Abel</hi> Gods cauſe prevailed by bringing down vengeance upon <hi>Cain</hi> the murtherer, <hi>the blood of thy brother crieth to me from the ground,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen, 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>and therefore now thou art curſed from the earth.</hi> The Martyrs periſhed in the cauſe of God, and yet even in their deaths that cauſe prevailed by bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vengeance upon the perſecutors: <hi>I ſaw under the altar the ſouls of them that were ſlain for the word of God, and for the teſtimony which they held, and they cried with a loud voice, how long, O Lord
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:156219:25"/>holy and true, doſt thou not avenge our blood on them that dwell on the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 6.10.</note> Wee need not doubt this prevailing of the cauſe of God in our neighbouring Kingdom, how ever it may ſeeme for the time to goe downe in the barbarous and bloudy deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of that poore people, whoſe bloud cryes ſo loud from the ground, as God cannot but curſe the murtherers; and whoſe ſoules under the Altar cry ſo loud, as God cannot but judge and avenge their bloud on them who have ſo inhumanely and ſo unmercifully ſhed it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By way of improvement; that cauſe prevails that improves it ſelfe by the oppoſition and violence it ſuffers under. Gods cauſe, like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> is victorious even then when we think it has received its deaths wound; and like the Camomill,<note place="margin">Eſ. 53.10. Ex. 1.12. Cum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicantur lateres, venit Moſes. Eſt. 8.16 Da. 6.26. Ezr. 6.6.</note> it ſpreads more by being trampled upon; or like the fire, the more it is ſmothered and kept in by violence for the time, the more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible it breaks out and heats afterwards. In ſhedding the bloud of Chriſt, the cauſe of God ſeemed to ſuffer; but you know what an improvement it received by it, that bloud was it, that was the fruitfull field of ſuch a ſeed unto God; <hi>'twas making his ſoul an offering for ſin that made him ſee his ſeed.</hi> In <hi>Egypt</hi> the cauſe of God ſeem'd to ſuffer, when the children were commanded to be deſtroyed and their burthens were doubled, yet we know that decree increaſed the people, and doubling of their taskes haſted their deliverance. By the oppoſitions of <hi>Haman</hi> the cauſe of God got better footing: And by caſting <hi>Daniel</hi> into the Lions den, God came everywhere to be more feared and worſhipt by a publike decree: By the oppoſitions of <hi>Tatnai</hi> and <hi>Shetherboz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai</hi> the building of Gods houſe proſpered: In burning and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the martyrs in the primitive times, and in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, the cauſe of <hi>God</hi> ſeemd to ſuffer, yet we know how Martyrdom improves it, the bloud of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Church, that is, as the Biſhop of <hi>Valence</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">To the King of France in a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at Fountain Bleau. So Tert. ad Scàp. Quiſque enim tan tam tole. rantiam ſpectans, ut aliquo ſcrupulo percuſſus &amp; onqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenditur quid ſis in cauſa Et ubi cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem ipſe ſtatim ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur.</note> once explained it; people by ſeeing the ſufferings of the Martyrs, came more to look into and underſtand that profeſſion then formerly they had done, which made them with ſo much patience indure ſuch torments, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:156219:26"/>ſo at length to imbrace the ſame; like the generating of the Phoenix, out of the aſhes not the egges of the Damme: Out of the aſhes of a few Saints multitudes of profeſſours ariſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall preſent you theſe few grounds of this truth,<note place="margin">reaſons of the point.</note> to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged in your owne private meditations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The genius of Religion, it is of a flouriſhing and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nature: As one ſaid of <hi>Anthony</hi> that was at oddes with <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus,</hi> compound with him, for his genius goes beyond yours: The genius of Religion goes beyond that of all its oppoſites. It was firſt in families, after in Cities, and ſo by degrees ſpread it ſelf over the world. <hi>The image in Nebuchadnezzars viſion was ſmitten by a ſtone cut out without hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2.34, 35.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſtone that ſmote the image became a great Mountaine, and fill'd the earth:</hi> You have the interpretation of this in the following verſes, the Image in its ſeverall parts repreſented the 4. Monarchies of the world: which ſhould all bee deſtroyed by a fift Kingdome, which Chriſt ſhould ſet up, which ſhould ſo improve it ſelfe from a ſmall beginning, as quickly to fill the whole earth, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all oppoſitions made againſt it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The power of Chriſt, he is able to ſet up his colours and his Scepter there where no earthly King dares ſet his foot.<note place="margin">Pritan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notum in acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manis Joca, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto verò ſub aita</note> 'Twas <hi>Tertullians</hi> obſervation, <hi>Britaine</hi> was a place which the <hi>Romanes</hi> could not at ſuch a time poſſeſſe, and yet it was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued to Chriſt. Look by what motives people are brought in to Chriſt, you muſt needs acknowledge a ſtrong working pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er above all the ſtrengths of men, done by ſuch contrary wayes to fleſh and bloud: If wee will follow Chriſt, and be heyres of heaven, <hi>Wee muſt deny our ſelves, and take up our Croſſe and ſuffer perſecution and be hated for his name ſake, and hate father and mother, &amp;c.</hi> and yet by theſe and the like motives more are brought in to Chriſt and ſubmit to his Lawes, then by all the rewards could be propoſed to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The courſe of Gods providence, which ſhall ſtill uphold it, ſo as to give it footing more and more every day: though the Revelation be obſcure in many things, yet this we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:156219:26"/>out of it clearly, that when the vialls begin to be powred out, the truth ſhall grow up to the confuſion of its enemies; as on the other ſide, wee ſee ſeverall effects of Gods providence againſt the Kingdome of Satan and Antichriſt: that where we ſee the falſe Religion hath received ſome blowes, we may aſſure our ſelves, a further ruine will certainely follow, as they ſaid of <hi>Haman, If Mordecai be of the ſeed of the Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heſt. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>before whom thou haſt begun to fall, thou ſhalt not prevaile againſt him, but ſhalt ſurely fall before him:</hi> If Religion be of the ſeed of Chriſt, the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of God, falſe Religions, that once begin to fall, ſhall not prevaile, but ſhall ſurely fall before it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> It diſcovers the folly of thoſe that ſet themſelves againſt Gods people and Gods cauſes; let them take heed what they doe, ſuch ſet themſelves againſt Chriſt and his Kingdome and their attempts ſhall not proſper:<note place="margin">Iob 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>Hath any man hardned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt God, and proſpered?</hi> I muſt ſay to ſuch as <hi>Abijah</hi> did to <hi>Ieroboam, Ye think to withſtand the Kingdome of the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chr. 13.8.</note> Let us not thinke we ſhall be able to withſtand the Kingdome of Chriſt, hee is able to breake through all oppoſitions, hee can cruſh his enemies, <hi>thou ſhalt breake them with an iron rod, thou ſhalt daſh them in pieces like a potters veſſell:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord at thy right hand ſhall ſtrike thorow Kings in the day of his wrath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 110.5.</note> Kings that be his enemies. It was part of <hi>Moſes</hi> Song touching the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Iſrael, <hi>the people ſhall heare and bee afraid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 15.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſorrow ſhall take hold on the inhabitants of Palestina, the Dukes of Edom ſhall be amazed, trembling ſhall take hold of the mighty men of Moab, the inhabitants of Canaan ſhall melt away, feare and dread ſhall fall upon them, for the Lord reignes for ever and ever.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt reignes, ſuch ſhall be the end of all his enemies, however they may flouriſh for a time. Oh! feare to oppoſe Chriſt in his Goſpel, in his people, in his cauſes.<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.9</note> 
               <hi>Woe unto him that ſtrives with his Maker, let the potſheards ſtrive with the potſheards of the earth.</hi> Let man ſtrive with man, and Prince fight with Prince, that's but daſhing one earthen pitcher againſt another, but let us take heed of ingaging Chriſt againſt us, woe to him that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:156219:27"/>ſtrives with Chriſt; 'tis dangerous ſetting our ſelves againſt his Kingdome, or his people, or his cauſes, leſt as <hi>in this mountaine,</hi> in Gods Church <hi>the hand of the Lord ſhall reſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Moab,</hi> all the enemies of Chriſt <hi>be troden downe under him, as ſtraw is trodden downe for the dunghill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Here's matter of great encouragement to thoſe that with upright hearts ſide with Chriſt, and ſet in to advance his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they ſhall proſper in the worke. We muſt not be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled though we finde great enemies and great oppoſitions; let us not value religion and the cauſe of Chriſt any whit the cheaper, becauſe ſo much ſet againſt. The Romanes held their land about the City of <hi>Rome</hi> at as deare a rate, when <hi>Hanniball</hi> beſieg'd it, as they did before. Prize Religion as high in times of trouble as in times of peace. Wee muſt not look only at the preſent proceedings, our ſpirits muſt not riſe or fall, onely as wee ſee a floud or an ebbe in the handling of Gods cauſes: but conſider the end, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes of the upright man,<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.37.</note> 
               <hi>mark his end, the end of that man is peace.</hi> Whatever the preſent condition ſhould prove to bee of Chriſts Kingdome, yet the end of it will be peace and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to Gods people. At <hi>Cannae</hi> the Romanes went to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate the Conſul that fled from the battaile, becauſe hee ſignified thereby, that the ſtate of things was not yet ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, but he durſt live: We ſhould not deſpaire of the ſtate of Gods Church and Religion, though we ſhould ſee them brought to great ſtraits. It may be we ſhall not ſee the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Gods Church in our dayes: yet here's comfort enough, to know the work ſhall go on: It is a worke in Chriſts hand, and a worke God takes pleaſure in,<note place="margin">Iſa. 53 10</note> 
               <hi>and the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1.16</note> Chriſt, who <hi>holds the ſtars in his Right hand,</hi> the Angels of his Church, to preſerve them, does cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly hold the Church it ſelfe, for whoſe good, his Miniſters are in his right hand, to preſerve her, whatever oppoſitions be made againſt her. At <hi>Antioch,</hi> if I miſtake not, the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall ſtory ſayes, there being an Earth quake, wherby many
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:156219:27"/>houſes fell, and the people terrified with it; being ready to forſake the city, one had a viſion, that he faw a man comming to him, who commanded him to write upon every houſe, <hi>Chriſtus nobiſcum,</hi> Chriſt is with us, ſtay here, and ſo it ceaſed: thus we ſhould do, when we conſider the tottering eſtate of religion, remember Chriſt is with us, be not affrighted, forſake it not, if God be for us, who can be againſt us? if Chriſt be in the ſhip with us, it cannot ſink.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially it may be high encouragement to you (Honourable and beloved:) you are they that muſt help up Chriſt into his Kingdom in the midſt of theſe great oppoſitions that are now made againſt it: we the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God can but encourage &amp; ſtrengthen you, as the Prophet; <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai</hi> and <hi>Zachary,</hi> Gods Prophets <hi>were with the Princes helping them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 5.2.</note> hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them with their prayers, and helping them with their inſtructions touching Gods will, and helping them with their exhortations to ſtirre them up; but the work is chiefly yours, you are to encounter Chriſts enemies, the ſword of juſtice is put into your hands to cut down all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. If your hearts be upright with God, that your conſciences aſſure you, you ſeek Gods glory, and the advancement of Chriſts Kingdom, not your ſelves, nor your own ends, you have as much encouragement as can be; you go on in a work that ſhall be carried up againſt all oppoſitions.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.27.</note> Should viſible means faile, yet as there is an <hi>inviſible God</hi> who may be ſeen by the eye of faith, ſo there are alſo inviſible means: the power of Chriſt ſhall reſt upon thoſe that work his works, and ſtand up faithfully in his cauſes. Should you be left fewer then you are, yet if you can but reſolve, when others forſake Chriſt, to ſay truly, <hi>Lord we will never forſake thee,</hi> and do it; not only ſay it: ſome have ſaid it, and yet with <hi>Peter</hi> gone away and deſerted the cauſe: there is then no reaſon why you ſhould fear, Chriſt can work by few as well as by many: Chriſt, when men faile, will tread the wine-preſſe alone, <hi>when the day of vengeance comes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 63.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>and the yeare of his redeemed ones comes, then, if there be none to help, his own arme will bring ſalvation.</hi> Do you what you can in a right way for Gods cauſes &amp; Chriſts Kingdom; and when you can do no more, ſtand ſtill and look on with griefe, that you can do no more; and if you can contribute nothing elſe, yet <hi>date lachrymulam,</hi> ſhed a teare: God puts the teares of his people into his bottle, and in his time teares ſhall be like the water that turnes and drives the wheele; Gods work ſhall go on, and your teares ſhall help to drive it on, as well as your nobleſt works. It was Gods word in a work that met with greater oppoſition then yours now can:<note place="margin">Exod. 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord.</hi> It may be your ſtrengths of the arme of fleſh may yet be too great for God to work by: <hi>the Lord ſaveth, not by ſword,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.47.</note> 
               <hi>nor by ſpeare, for the battell is the Lords. Gideon</hi> had too many, <hi>while he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:156219:28"/>had above three hundred:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 7.4</note> greatneſſe of outward ſtrength ecclipſes and darkens the glory of Chriſts power in ſaving: <hi>when God ſeeth that his peoples power is gone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.36.</note> then he ſtrikes into the work and more ſhewes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Let us not limit the holy One of Iſrael, neither to meanes, nor to times: whether there be many or few that ſtand up in Gods cauſes, wee are ſure of this, <hi>Chriſt ſhal reign till he hath put al his enemies under his feet.</hi> We look too much on the inſtruments,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.25.</note> &amp; are ready to cry out, <hi>if the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the earth be ſhaken, what ſhall the righteous do?</hi> you are they that are our foundations,<note place="margin">Pſ. 11.3.</note> you the preſervers of the fundamental laws of the ſtate and the preſervers of the fundamentall laws of the Church; if you be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, it will indeed be a ſad time to Gods righteous people; yet let not that affright us neither, we have a ſtronger foundation, <hi>fundamentum funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti,</hi> the foundation of the foundations; the head ſtone of the corner, the rock upon which the Church is built, which ſhall never be ſhaken. Goe you on therefore, and let every one faithfully do his duty to Chriſt and leave the iſſue to God.</p>
            <p>To conclude all; this day is a day of humiliation, and therfore a day of covenanting with God. O that I might now engage you all here preſent this day in this covenant, to take Chriſt for your King into your own hearts, and then to ſet faithfully to this work of undertaking his cauſes againſt all thoſe great oppoſitions which every day ſhew themſelves, when <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jada</hi> made the covenant with the Lord,<note place="margin">2 King. 11.17.</note> 
               <hi>that the people ſhould be the Lords people,</hi> 'twas to this end, that they ſhould undertake the Lords cauſes againſt the Lords enemies, <hi>for preſently they brake downe the houſe of Baal, and his altar, and his images, and ſlew Mattan the Prieſt of Baal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the altar.</hi> Let us make ſuch a covenant to be the Lords people, and ſo to undertake the Lords cauſes, as <hi>Scipio</hi> once held the poynt of his ſword to the breſts of many gallants that were flying out of <hi>Italy,</hi> and made them ſweare upon that ſword, that they would not deſert the cauſe: God has great cauſes now, Chriſt was never more engaged in great affaires then at this time: O that I might perſwade all that profeſſe themſelves Gods people, to engage themſelves to Chriſt; to make vowes betwixt God and their own ſoules upon theſe ſacred truths, this book, never to deſert Chriſts cauſes, but as faithfull ſubjects of his Kingdom, doe all they can, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all oppoſitions, to make Chriſts Kingdom flouriſh through the world,<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.23.</note> and remember <hi>Meroz</hi> curſe upon thoſe <hi>that come not to the help of Chriſt againſt the mighty.</hi> Chriſt can carry on his work without us: but if we doe not our part, <hi>deliverance ſhall come ſome other way,</hi> as <hi>Mord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cai</hi> told Queen <hi>Heſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſt. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>but wee ſhall be deſtroyed;</hi> the curſe will be upon every of us, that ſet not in every one in his way, and as God calls him to it, to ſet up Chriſt in the midſt of his enemies.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
